环
Uni
环球
Univer
环球私
Universal
环球私人
Universal Ci
环球私人影
Universal Cine
环球私人影咖
Universal Cinema
双倍赔偿
啊，你好啊，奈夫先生
Why, hello there, Mr. Neff.
工作到很晚啊，奈夫先生？
Working pretty late, aren't you, Mr. Neff?
是很晚,上去吧
Late enough. Let's ride.
-你看来面色很差     -我没事
You look kind of all in, at that. I'm fine.
-保险生意如何，奈夫先生？   -很好
How is the insurance business, Mr. Neff? Okay.
他们不肯卖我保险
They wouldn't ever sell me any.
他们说我的心难以捉摸
They said I have something loose in my heart.
-我心脏确实不好    -是吗?
I say it's rheumatism. Yeah?
12楼
Twelve.
办公室备忘录
Office memorandum.
沃特.奈夫致巴顿.基斯，索赔经理
Walter Neff to Barton Keyes, Claims Manager.
洛杉矶，1938年7月16日
Los Angeles, July 16, 1938.
亲爱的基斯
Dear Keyes...
我猜你听到后会说这是招认
I suppose you'll call this a confession when you hear it.
其实，我不喜欢  "招认"  这词
Well, I don't like the word confession.
我只是想让你了解一些事情的真相
I just want to set you right about something you couldn't see...
毕竟你正在为之头疼
because it was smack up against your nose.
你以为自己是个一流索赔经理
You think you're such a hot potato as a Claims Manager...
能一眼看穿虚假索赔
such a wolf on a phony claim.
也许你确实是，但是看看迪崔克森的案子
Maybe you are, but let's take a look at that Dietrichson claim.
意外和双倍赔偿
Accident and double indemnity.
这事儿上你曾表现不错，基斯
You were pretty good in there for a while, Keyes.
你说那不是意外。说对了。
You said it wasn't an accident. Check.
你说那不是自杀。说对了。
You said it wasn't suicide. Check.
你说那是谋杀。说对了。
You said it was murder. Check.
你感觉十拿九稳了，是吗？
You thought you had it cold, didn't you?
真相用包装纸包裹，附加粉红蝴蝶结
All wrapped up in tissue paper, with pink ribbons around it.
堪称完美
It was perfect.
但却不是，因为你犯了个错
Except it wasn't, because you made one mistake...
只一个小小错误
just one little mistake.
到确定凶手的那步，你搞错了人
When it came to picking the killer, you picked the wrong guy.
你想知道是谁杀了迪崔克森？
You want to know who killed Dietrichson?
拿稳你的廉价雪茄，基斯
Hold tight to that cheap cigar of yours, Keyes.
我杀了迪崔克森
I killed Dietrichson.
我，沃特.奈夫，保险推销员
Me, Walter Neff, insurance salesman.
35岁，未婚，没有前科
35 years old, unmarried, no visible scars...
直至不久之前，我是说
until a while ago, that is.
对，我杀了他
Yes, I killed him.
我杀他是为了钱...
I killed him for money...
和一个女人
and for a woman.
而我没得到钱，而我没得到那女人
And I didn't get the money and I didn't get the woman.
很有趣，是吧？
Pretty, isn't it?
一切始于去年5月
It all began last May.
那是5月底了
Around the end of May, it was.
我去了格伦戴尔
I'd been out to Glendale
送一些乳业卡车的保单
to deliver a policy on some dairy trucks.
回来路上
On the way back
我记起洛斯菲利大道有宗汽车续保的事
I remembered this auto renewal near Los Feliz Boulevard.
于是我开车过去
So I drove over there.
那是一幢那种十来年前人们热衷的...
It was one of those California Spanish houses...
加州-西班牙风格房子
everyone was nuts about 10 or 15 years ago.
这一幢一定让某人花了3万块
This one must've cost somebody about $30,000.
那是说，他已经付款完毕的话
That is, if he ever finished paying for it.
迪崔克森先生在吗？
Is Mr. Dietrichson in?
-谁要找他？    -我叫奈夫，沃特.奈夫
Who wants to see him? My name is Neff. Walter Neff.
如果你想推销...
If you're selling something...
你看，我是想跟迪崔克森先生谈...
Look, it's Mr. Dietrichson I want to talk to...
不是来收杂志费的
and it's not magazine subscriptions.
-听着，迪崔克森先生不在家     -他多久回来？
Listen, Mr. Dietrichson is not in. How soon do you expect him?
他回来时就回来了，这么说有用吗？
He'll be home when he gets here, if that's any help to you.
什么事，妮蒂？是谁？
What is it, Nettie? Who is it?
有人来找迪崔克森先生
It's for Mr. Dietrichson.
我是迪崔克森太太，什么事？
I'm Mrs. Dietrichson. What is it?
你好，迪崔克森太太
How do you do, Mrs. Dietrichson?
我是沃特.奈夫，太平洋保险的
I'm Walter Neff, Pacific All Risk.
-太平洋什么？   -太平洋保险公司
Pacific all what? The Pacific All Risk Insurance Company.
是汽车保险续保的事
It's about some renewals on the automobiles.
过去两星期里...
I've been trying to contact your husband
我一直想联系你先生
for the past two weeks...
-但他从不在办公室    -我能做些什么？
but he's never in his office. Is there anything I can do?
保险15号到期
The insurance ran out on the 15th.
我不愿去想象...
I'd hate to think of your having a smashed fender...
您出什么状况却无任何保险...
or something while you're not...
这种情况
fully covered.
也许我明白您的意思，奈夫先生
Perhaps I know what you mean, Mr. Neff.
-我正在晒日光浴   -希望附近没鸽子
I've just been taking a sunbath. No pigeons around, I hope.
关于那些保单，
About those policies,
迪崔克森太太，抱歉打扰您，但是...
Mrs. Dietrichson, I hate to take up your time, but...
没关系
Oh, that's all right.
如果您能稍等我更衣，我马上下来
If you'll wait till I put something on, I'll be right down.
妮蒂，带奈夫先生到客厅
Nettie, show Mr. Neff into the living room.
客厅会在哪儿？
Where would the living room be?
那里，但他们把酒锁起来了
In there, but they keep the liquor locked up.
没关系，我一向自有办法
It's all right. I always carry my own keys.
客厅依然充斥着...
The living room was still stuffy...
昨晚的雪茄气味
from last night's cigars.
窗户紧闭...
The windows were closed...
阳光从百叶窗透射进来...
and the sunshine coming in through the venetian blinds...
让空气中的尘埃显现
showed up the dust in the air.
钢琴上，几个精致相框里，
On the piano, in a couple of fancy frames,
是迪崔克森先生和萝拉...
were Mr. Dietrichson and Lola...
他和第一位妻子的女儿
his daughter by his first wife.
他们有一缸那种小红金鱼...
They had a bowl of those little red goldfish...
放在大沙发后面的桌子上
on the table behind the big davenport.
但说实话，基斯
But to tell you the truth, Keyes...
我当时对金鱼毫无兴趣
I wasn't a whole lot interested in goldfish right then.
对汽车续保、迪崔克森先生和他女儿萝拉也是
Or in auto renewals, or in Mr. Dietrichson and his daughter Lola.
我一心想着楼上那女的
I was thinking about that dame upstairs,
以及之前她看我的方式
and the way she had looked at me...
我想再见到她，近一些...
and I wanted to see her again, close...
而不是隔着那蠢楼梯
without that silly staircase between us.
-没让您久等吧？   -一点没有，迪崔克森太太
I wasn't long, was I? Not at all, Mrs. Dietrichson.
-希望我脸色还好    -很完美，在我看来
Hope I've got my face on straight. It's perfect, for my money.
-你叫奈夫是吧？   -对
Neff is the name, isn't it? Yeah.
两个F，像费城那样，如果你知道那故事...
With two "F's," like in Philadelphia, if you know the story.
-什么故事？     -费城故事啊
What story? The Philadelphia Story.
不如坐下，你谈谈保险的事
Suppose we sit down and you tell me about the insurance.
我丈夫什么也不告诉我
My husband never tells me anything.
是关于你们的两部车，那凯迪拉克和克莱斯勒
Well, it's on your two cars, the LaSalle and the Plymouth.
我们为迪崔克森先生负责这单保险...
We've been handling this insurance for Mr. Dietrichson
已三年了
for three years...
我们不希望出现断供情况
and we'd hate to see the policies lapse.
你的脚链很别致啊，迪崔克森太太
That's a honey of an anklet you're wearing, Mrs. Dietrichson.
我刚说过，我们不希望保单断供
As I was saying, we'd hate to see the policies lapse.
当然 ，
Of course,
我们有三十天宽限期，最多了
we give them 30 days. That's all we're allowed to give.
我猜他是在长滩的油田那边太忙了
I guess he's been too busy down at Long Beach in the oil fields.
我能哪天晚上和他谈几分钟吗？
Couldn't I catch him at home some evening for a few minutes?
应该可以， 但他8点前很少回家
I suppose so. But he's never home much before 8:00.
我倒没问题
That's fine with me.
你和汽车俱乐部没关系吧？
You're not connected with the Automobile Club, are you?
没，我是太平洋保险，怎么了？
No, the All Risk, Mrs. Dietrichson. Why?
有个汽车俱乐部的人一直在找他
Somebody from the Automobile Club has been trying to get him.
-他们的性价比更好吗？   -如果你丈夫是会员的话
Do they have a better rate? If your husband's a member.
他不是
No, he isn't.
那，他得先加入会员
Well, then he'd have to join the club
先交会员费
and pay the membership fee to start with.
我从不抢人买卖，迪崔克森太太
I never knock the other fellow's merchandise, Mrs. Dietrichson.
汽车俱乐部服务很好
The Automobile Club's fine.
但我的服务也很好
I can do just as well for you, though.
我这份保单很有吸引力
I have a very attractive policy here.
两分钟都用不了...
It wouldn't take me two minutes
就能向您丈夫解释明白
to put it in front of your husband.
举个例子，我们有个新规，撞车赔偿...
For instance, we're writing a new kind of 50% retention feature...
有50％保留额度
in the collision coverage.
你是个聪明的保险员，是吗？
You're a smart insurance man, aren't you, Mr. Neff?
-我已经入行11年     -干的不错？
Well, I've been at it 11 years. Doing pretty well?
够谋生了
It's a living.
你只做汽车保险还是全部都做？
You handle just automobile insurance, or all kinds?
全部。火灾险，地震险，盗窃险，
All kinds. Fire, earthquake, theft,
公共债务，集体保险...
public liability, group insurance...
工业事故等等，无所不包
industrial stuff and so on, right down the line.
意外保险？
Accident insurance?
意外保险？当然了，迪崔克森太太
Accident insurance? Sure, Mrs. Dietrichson.
希望您告诉我那脚链上刻的什么？
Wish you'd tell me what's engraved on that anklet.
-只是我的名字    -未请教？
Just my name. As, for instance?
-菲莉丝    -菲莉丝啊？
Phyllis. Phyllis, huh?
-我想我很喜欢  -但你不确定？
I think I like that. But you're not sure?
我得开上几圈才知道
I'd have to drive it around the block a couple of times.
奈夫先生，不如你明天晚上八点半左右来
Mr. Neff, why don't you drop by tomorrow evening around 8:30?
-他会在家    -谁？
He'll be in then. Who?
我丈夫啊，你不是着急想跟他谈吗？
My husband. You were anxious to talk to him, weren't you?
是，曾经是，但我又觉得那不重要了...
Yeah, I was, but I'm sort of getting over the idea...
如果你懂我意思
if you know what I mean.
这个州可是限速啊，奈夫先生。每小时45英里
There's a speed limit in this state, Mr. Neff. 45 miles an hour.
-我时速多少，警官？    -我得说快90了
How fast was I going, officer? I'd say around 90.
我猜你要下摩托给我罚单啊
Suppose you get down off your motorcycle and give me a ticket.
我猜我这次就警告后放行吧
Suppose I let you off with a warning this time.
我猜我不会听警告
Suppose it doesn't take.
我猜我会给你一拳
Suppose I have to whack you over the knuckles.
我猜我会嚎啕大哭，趴在你的肩膀上
Suppose I bust out crying and put my head on your shoulder.
我猜你会想趴在我丈夫肩膀上
Suppose you try putting it on my husband's shoulder.
那拉倒吧
That tears it.
-明晚八点半     -那正是我说的
8:30 tomorrow evening then. That's what I suggested.
-你也会在家？    - 应该是，一般都会
Will you be here, too? I guess so, I usually am.
相同椅子，相同香水，相同脚链？
Same chair, same perfume, same anklet?
我不确定是否明白你的意思
I wonder if I know what you mean.
我不确定你是否真不确定
I wonder if you wonder.
那是个炎热的下午...
It was a hot afternoon and I can still remember...
至今我仍记得沿街金银花的味道
the smell of honeysuckle all along that street.
我怎么会知道谋杀有时...
How could I have known that murder can sometimes
闻起来像是金银花？
smell like honeysuckle?
也许你会知道，基斯...
Maybe you would have known, Keyes...
当她提到意外险的时候，但我没意识到
the minute she mentioned accident insurance, but I didn't.
我心情愉快
I felt like a million.
我回办公室，看是否有邮件
I went back to the office to see if I had any mail.
就是有个英格伍德卡车司机
It was the day you had that truck driver
来找你的那天
from Inglewood on the carpet.
记得吗，基斯？
Remember, Keyes?
奈夫先生，基斯先生想见你
Mr. Neff, Mr. Keyes wants to see you.
他嚷着要找你一下午了
He's been yelling for you all afternoon.
他是不是只想找人发发火？
Is he sore, or just frothing at the mouth a little?
帮我放好，好吗？
Park this for me, will you, sweetheart?
-嗨，沃特    -嗨，乔治
Hello, Walter. Hi, George.
拜托，戈罗皮
Come on. Come on, Garlopis.
你别想忽悠任何人
You're not kidding anybody with that line of bull.
-你走投无路了，你知道。  -那是你说的。
You're in a jam and you know it. Says you.
-我只要我的钱。   -那是你说的
All I want is my money. Says you.
你只会招来警察。嗨，沃特
All you're gonna get is the cops. Hello, Walter.
-这是英格伍德来的山姆.戈罗皮    -我认识戈罗皮先生
This is Sam Garlopis from Inglewood. Sure, I know Mr. Garlopis.
帮他写过卡车保单。你好吗，戈罗皮先生？
Wrote a policy on his truck. How are you, Mr. Garlopis?
-我不好，卡车被烧了    -对，听着
I ain't so good. My truck burned down. Yeah. Now look, Garlopis.
我每个月都收到上百份索赔
Every month hundreds of claims come to this desk.
有些是假的，我一看就知道
Some of them are phonies, and I know which ones.
怎么知道？我的小人儿告诉我的
How do I know? Because my little man tells me.
-什么小人儿？   -在这里的小人儿
What little man? The little man in here.
每次一有虚假索赔出现
Every time one of these phonies comes along,
他就在我胃里打个结
it ties knots in my stomach.
我就吃不了饭
I can't eat.
你就是其中一个结
Yours is one of them, Garlopis.
所以我知道你是虚假索赔
That's how I knew your claim was crooked.
那我怎么办了呢？
So what did I do?
下午我派了拖车去你车库...
I sent a tow car over to your garage this afternoon...
他们抬起了你那烧掉的卡车
and they jacked up that burned-out truck of yours.
他们发现了什么呢？
And what did they find?
他们找到一堆碎屑的余烬
They found what was left of a neat pile of shavings.
什么碎屑？
What shavings?
你浸过油，又扔上火柴的那些
The ones you soaked with kerosene and dropped a match on.
你看，先生，我只是个穷人，也许犯了错
Look, Mister, I'm just a poor guy. Maybe I made a mistake.
这算是一种说法
That's one way of putting it.
我感觉不好，基斯先生
I ain't feeling so good, Mr. Keyes.
这里，签了字你感觉就会好了
Here. Just a minute. Sign this and you'll feel fine.
-签什么？    -放弃索赔声明，这里
Sign what? It's a waiver on your claim. Right here.
-这里？   -这里
Here? Here.
现在你又有诚信了。 再见
Now you're an honest man again. Goodbye, Garlopis.
但我没卡车了
But I ain't got no more truck.
在我那片儿，2600是笔大钱
$2,600 is lot of dough where I live.
怎么了，戈罗皮？你不会开门吗？
What's the matter, Garlopis, don't you know how to open the door?
将手放在把手上，向左转动
Just put your hand on the knob, turn it to the left.
拉向自己
Now pull it toward you.
-对了     -谢谢，基斯先生
That's the boy. Thank you, Mr. Keyes.
我们算是干嘛的？
What kind of an outfit is this, anyway?
是保险公司...
Are we an insurance company,
还是一群门外汉...
or just a bunch of dimwitted amateurs...
竟给这种人保险？
to write a policy on a mug like that?
等等，基斯，他不是我评估的
Now, wait a minute, Keyes. I don't rate this beef.
我在戈罗皮的申请表上标注了...
I clipped a note to that Garlopis application...
同意他的申请之前...
to have him thoroughly investigated...
要做详细评估.     -我知道，沃特
before we accepted the risk. I know you did, Walter.
我不是针对你
I'm not beefing at you.
我是说公司。他们做事的方式就是...
It's the company. It's the way they do things.
什么事也不做！
The way they don't do things!
就为了满足销售额
The way they'll write anything
胡写乱填一通
just to get it down on the sales sheet.
而我就是那个...
And I'm the guy
在这梗着脖子紧盯虚假索赔的人
that has to sit here up to my neck in phony claims...
来防止...
so they won't
他们从窗户扔出去的钱比从门外带来的还多
throw more money out the window than they take in at the door.
这页揭过去，下个话题吧
Okay, turn the record over, let's hear the other side.
我受够了给一群...
Well, I get darn sick of trying to
口若悬河的销售员擦屁股了
pick up after a gang of fast-talking salesmen...
他们能蠢到将人身险卖给...
dumb enough to sell life insurance to a guy...
和四条响尾蛇睡一个被窝的人
who sleeps in the same bed with four rattlesnakes.
沃特，我干这个26年了，我告诉你...
Walter, I've had 26 years of this and let me tell you,
我变的...
I'm getting...
你每分钟都乐在其中，基斯
Yeah, and you've loved every minute of it, Keyes.
你爱这行当
You love it,
你只是太紧张了，你和你的小人儿
only you worry about it too darn much, you and your little man.
你太过谨慎行事，会把自己搞疯的
You're so darn conscientious, you're driving yourself crazy.
你不看日历来确定...
You wouldn't even say today is Tuesday
都不敢说今天是周二
unless you looked at the calendar.
然后你还得检查那是今年的...
Then you'd check to see if it was this year's
还是去年的日历
or last year's calendar.
你还得研究日历是哪里印的
Then you'd find out who printed the calendar...
看他们是否...
and find out if their calendar
能对上世界标准日历
checked with the World Almanac's calendar.
够了,沃特
Now, that's enough from you, Walter.
在我扔桌子砸你之前，快滚
Now, get out of here before I throw my desk at you.
我也爱你
I love you, too.
我是说真的，你这老家伙...
I really did, too, you old crab...
总是大叫大嚷，对人呼来喝去
always yelling your head off, always sore at everybody.
但你这些花招从来都骗不了我
But you never fooled me with your song and dance. Not for a second.
可以说我一直知道，在你那满是烟灰的马甲之后...
I kind of always knew that behind the cigar ashes on your vest...
你有颗房子那么大的心
you had a heart as big as a house.
我回到办公室，电话有留言
Back in my office there was a phone message
迪崔克森太太的
from Mrs. Dietrichson...
关于续保
about the renewals.
她又不让我第二天晚上去了
She didn't want me to come tomorrow evening.
想让我周四下午3点半去
She wanted me to come Thursday afternoon at 3:30 instead.
我周四下午日程排的满满的
I had a lot of stuff lined up for that Thursday afternoon...
包括得去趟圣塔莫妮卡
including a trip down to Santa Monica...
去推销一些集体保险
to see a couple of live prospects about some group insurance.
但我总是想着菲莉丝.迪崔克森
But I kept thinking about Phyllis Dietrichson...
和那脚链戴在她腿上的样子
and the way that anklet of hers cut into her leg.
嗨，奈夫先生，你不进来吗？
Hello, Mr. Neff. Aren't you coming in?
我在考虑
I'm considering it.
希望你别介意我改了时间
I hope you didn't mind my changing the appointment.
-昨晚不太方便     -没关系
Last night wasn't so convenient. That's all right.
反正我只是在弄我的集邮册
I was working on my stamp collection anyway.
我在弄冰茶，你要一杯吗？
I was just fixing some iced tea. Would you like a glass?
好，除非你有多余的啤酒
Yeah, unless you've got a bottle of beer that's not working.
也许有，我从不知道冰箱里有什么
There may be some. I never know what's in the icebox.
妮蒂
Nettie.
关于续保，奈夫先生，我跟丈夫谈过了
About those renewals, Mr. Neff. I talked to my husband about it.
-是吗？   -对，他说他会续保
Oh, you did? Yes. He'll renew with you, he told me so.
事实上，我以为他今天下午在家
As a matter of fact, I thought he'd be here this afternoon.
-但他不在？    -不在
But he's not? No.
真可惜
That's terrible.
妮蒂
Nettie!
哦，我忘了，今天女佣放假
Oh, I forgot, today's the maid's day off.
不用啤酒了，冰茶也行
Never mind the beer. Iced tea will be fine.
-柠檬？糖？     -按你的来吧
Lemon? Sugar? Fix it your way.
既然女佣放假，
As long as it's the maid's day off,
也许我能帮你做点什么。
maybe there's something I can do for you.
-例如吸尘。  -有趣
Like running the vacuum cleaner. Fresh.
我以前推销过吸尘器
I used to peddle vacuum cleaners.
赚得不多，但能学到很多人生哲理
Not much money, but you learn a lot about life.
我觉得那在课堂上可学不到
I didn't think you'd learned it from a correspondence course.
你在哪里养成喝茶的习惯？
Where'd you pick up this tea drinking?
-你不是英国人吧？     -不，我是加州人
You're not English, are you? No. Californian.
在洛杉矶土生土长
Born right here in Los Angeles.
他们说加州本地人都来自爱荷华
They say all native Californians come from Iowa.
-奈夫先生，我...     -叫我沃特
Mr. Neff, I... Make it Walter, huh?
-沃特     -是的
Walter. That's right.
告诉我，沃特
Tell me, Walter,
卖出保险后，你拿多少提成？
on this insurance, how much commission do you make?
20％，怎么了？
Twenty percent. Why?
我想也许我能再给你点生意
I thought perhaps I could throw a little more business your way.
-我不嫌多啊      -我想起我丈夫
I can always use it. I was thinking about my husband.
我很担心他在油田的工作
I worry a lot about him down in those oil fields.
-工作性质很危险    -身为管理人员不会吧？
It's very dangerous. Not for an executive, is it?
他不只是坐办公室
He doesn't just sit behind a desk.
他要跟钻油人员到油田
He's right down there with those drilling crews.
这令我担心不已
It's got me worried sick.
你是说，钻油塔可能倒了砸到他？
You mean, some dark night a crown block might fall on him?
-请别这么说    -就这么回事啊
Please don't talk like that. But that's the idea.
有一次一根管子击中了工头
The other day a casing line snapped and caught the foreman.
-他脊椎骨折住院了    -真糟糕
He's in the hospital with a broken back. That's bad.
我想起来就觉得不安
It's got me jittery just thinking about it.
如果我丈夫也遇上这种事呢
Suppose something like that happened to my husband.
有可能
It could. Well...
-你不认为他应该买意外险吗？   -嗯
don't you think he ought to have accident insurance? Mmm-hmm.
他买哪种险合适？
What kind of insurance could he have?
足够支付医疗费用的都行
Enough to cover doctors and hospital bills.
例如每周125现金保障
Say $125 a week cash benefit.
最高赔偿达5万元
And he'd rate around $50,000 capital sum.
-最高赔偿？什么意思？     -如果他死了
Capital sum? What's that? In case he gets killed.
也许我不该这么说
Maybe I shouldn't have said that.
我猜你做这一行要想得面面俱到
I suppose you have to think of everything in your business.
你丈夫会理解的
Well, your husband would understand.
我觉得我可以让他考虑...
I'm sure I could sell him on the idea of
购买意外险
some accident protection.
不如我跟他谈谈？
Why don't I talk to him about it?
你可以试试，但他很固执
You could try, but he's pretty tough-going.
人们起初都很固执
They're all tough at first.
他头脑很复杂
He has a lot on his mind.
他不懂什么是倾听...
He doesn't seem to want to listen to anything...
除了收音机里的棒球赛
except maybe a baseball game on the radio.
有时候我们坐个整晚
Sometimes we sit here all evening
相互之间却不吐一字
and never say a word to each other.
-听起来挺沉闷      -我只是坐这织毛衣
Sounds pretty dull. So, I just sit and knit.
你嫁他是为了这个吗？
Is that what you married him for?
也许我喜欢他手持毛线的样子
Maybe I like the way his thumbs hold up the wool.
如果他的手累了...
Anytime his thumbs get tired...
有我在，你不用织什么毛衣
Only, with me around, you wouldn't have to knit.
-不用吗？     -你尽管放心，不用
Wouldn't I? You bet your life, you wouldn't.
加点朗姆酒也许更好一点
Wonder if a little rum would get this up on its feet.
我想问你件事，沃特
I want to ask you something, Walter.
我能够不去打扰他...
Could I get an accident policy for him
而给他买份意外险吗？
without bothering him at all?
再说一次？
How's that, again?
这对你也更容易了
It would make it easier for you, too.
你都不用和他谈了
You wouldn't even have to talk to him.
我有点私房钱
I have a little allowance of my own.
我可以付款，他不用知道这事
I could pay for it and he needn't know anything about it.
为什么他不用知道？
Why shouldn't he know?
因为他不想要意外险
Because he doesn't want accident insurance.
他对此有点迷信
He's superstitious about it.
很多人都是。真有趣，对吗？
A lot of people are. That's funny, isn't it?
如果能那样办的话
If there was a way to get it like that,
能省掉不少麻烦
all the worry would be over.
-懂我意思吗，沃特？    -当然，我眼睛雪亮
See what I mean, Walter? Sure. I got good eyesight.
你是说，你希望他在不知情的情况下拥有保险
You mean you want him to have the policy without him knowing it.
那意味着，他不知情这事...
And that means without the insurance company knowing
保险公司那边也不能知道
that he doesn't know it.
-是这么设想的吧？   -有什么问题吗？
That's the setup, isn't it? Is there anything wrong with it?
没有，我看很好
No, I think it's lovely.
然后，如果某个雨夜，
Then, if some dark, wet night,
那钻油塔确实砸向他...
that crown block did fall on him...
什么钻油塔？
What crown block?
但有时钻油塔自己办不到
Only sometimes it can't quite make it on its own,
它得需要一点帮助
it has to have a little help.
我不知道你在说什么
I don't know what you're talking about.
当然，不一定非是钻油塔
Of course, it doesn't have to be a crown block.
也可能是汽车撞了他
It can be a car backing over him,
也可能从楼上窗口坠楼
or he could fall out of the upstairs window.
诸如此类，下面就是太平间接手了
Any little thing like that, just so it's a morgue job.
-你疯了？    -没那么疯
Are you crazy? Not that crazy.
-再见，迪崔克森太太    -怎么了？
Goodbye, Mrs. Dietrichson. What's the matter?
听着宝贝，你没法全身而退
Look, baby, you can't get away with it.
你想干掉他，不是吗？
You want to knock him off, don't you?
你太含血喷人了
That's a horrible thing to say.
你以为我是什么人?
What'd you think I was, anyway?
直接走进...
A guy that walks into
一个漂亮少妇家的客厅然后说：
a good looking dame's front parlor and says:
“下午好，我给做丈夫的卖意外险”
"Good afternoon, I sell accident insurance on husbands.
“您对您丈夫厌烦了吗？”
"You got one that's been around too long?
“是不是想将他变成钱？”
"One you'd like to turn into a little hard cash?
“对我笑一个 ，我就帮你搞定”
"Just give me a smile and I'll help you collect. "
-你认为我是蠢蛋啊    -我认为你是坏蛋
Boy, what a dope you must think I am. I think you're rotten.
我认为你很棒，只要我不是你丈夫
I think you're swell, so long as I'm not your husband.
-给我滚    -不用你说
Get out of here. You bet I'll get out of here, baby.
我会走的，尽快
I'll get out of here, but quick.
我态度坚决，直截了当
So I let her have it straight between the eyes.
我没上当，这次没有
She didn't fool me for a minute, not this time.
我知道这是个烫手山芋
I knew I had hold of a red-hot poker...
必须在烫烂我的手之前扔掉
and the time to drop it was before it burned my hand off.
我停在汽车餐厅，要了瓶啤酒
I stopped at a drive-in for a bottle of beer,
这半天一直想喝的
the one I had wanted all along...
现在更想了
only I wanted it worse now,
来除掉她那冰茶的味道
to get rid of the sour taste of her iced tea...
以及和它有关的一切
and everything that went with it.
我不想回办公室
I didn't want to go back to the office
就去了三街和西街...
so I dropped by a bowling alley...
的保龄球馆，打了几局...
at Third and Western and rolled a few lines...
使自己分散注意力
to get my mind thinking about something else for a while.
走时我没胃口吃饭
I didn't feel like eating dinner
也不想去什么娱乐
when I left, and I didn't feel like a show.
于是开车回家，停车，上楼
So, I drove home, put the car away and went up to my apartment.
天开始下雨，我眼看天色渐黑
It had begun to rain outside and I watched it get dark...
却连灯都没开
and didn't even turn on the light.
那也对我毫无帮助
That didn't help me either.
我心乱如麻
I was all twisted up inside...
烫手山芋还在我手里捧着
and I was still holding on to that red-hot poker.
当时我才意识到
And right then it came over me
我还一点都没走出来
that I hadn't walked out on anything at all.
那诱惑太过强烈...
That the hook was too strong...
我和她之间还没有结束
that this wasn't the end between her and me.
反而才刚刚开始
It was only the beginning.
所以，8点门铃响起...
So at 8:00 the bell would ring
我不假思索就知道来人是谁
and I'd know who it was without even having to think.
好像这是最自然不过的事
As if it was the most natural thing in the world.
嗨，你今天下午忘拿帽子
Hello. You forgot your hat this afternoon.
-是吗？     -不想让我拿进来吗？
Did I? Don't you want me to bring it in?
好
Sure.
放椅子上
Put it on the chair.
-你怎么知道我住址？    -电话薄
How'd you know where I live? It's in the phone book.
-正在下雨    -对
It's raining. Yeah.
脱下外衣坐下吧
Peel off your coat and sit down.
你丈夫出去了？
Your husband out?
对，长滩，要建一座新井
Yes. Long Beach. They're spudding in a new well.
他说晚点回来，大约9点半
He phoned he'd be late. About 9:30.
该说你很高兴见到我了吧？
It's about time you said you were glad to see me.
我知道你不会那样就拉倒的
I knew you wouldn't leave it like that.
-哪样？     -今天下午那样
Like what? Like it was this afternoon.
我一定是说错话
I must have said something
让你严重误会了
that gave you a terribly wrong impression.
你千万不能那么看我，沃特
You must never think anything like that about me, Walter.
-好的     -不好
Okay. No, it's not okay.
-如果你不信我就不好    -你想让我怎样？
Not if you don't believe me. What do you want me to do?
我想你对我好一些
I want you to be nice to me.
像你第一次来我家那样
Like the first time you came to the house.
回不去了
It can't be like the first time.
-发生了一些事    -我知道
Something's happened. I know it has.
在我们之间
It's happened to us.
我觉得他在盯着我，但不是出于关心
I feel as if he was watching me. Not that he cares. Not anymore.
他勒住我让我无法呼吸
He keeps me on a leash so tight I can't breathe.
他不是在长滩吗？放松
He's in Long Beach, isn't he? Relax.
也许我不该来
Maybe I oughtn't to have come.
-也许不该     -你想我走？
Maybe you oughtn't. You want me to go?
-如果你想     -现在？
If you want to. Right now?
当然，现在...
Sure, right now.
-我为你疯狂，宝贝     -我也为你疯狂，沃特
I'm crazy about you, baby. I'm crazy about you, Walter.
你头发上的香水，叫什么名字？
That perfume on your hair. What's the name of it?
我不知道，我在昂塞纳达买的
I don't know. I bought it in Ensenada.
你应该喝点那种玫瑰红葡萄酒来搭配
You ought to have some of that pink wine to go with it.
起泡的那种，但我只有波本
The kind that bubbles. All I got is bourbon.
波本也行啊，沃特
Bourbon is fine, Walter.
拿两个杯子，好吗？
Get a couple of glasses, will you?
-加苏打水？    -白水，谢谢
Club soda? Plain water, please.
知道吗？ 六个月前...
You know, about six months ago
有人在浴缸里踩肥皂滑倒
a guy slipped on a cake of soap in his bathtub...
摔晕了然后淹死了
and knocked himself cold and was drowned.
而他买了意外险
Only he had accident insurance.
他们验尸了，她就没跑掉
So they had an autopsy and she didn't get away with it.
-谁没跑掉？    -他老婆
Who didn't? His wife.
还有个男的被枪打死的保险案子
Then there was a case of a guy who was found shot.
他老婆说他在擦枪
His wife said he was cleaning a gun
不小心打中肚子
and his stomach got in the way.
最后她得到3平米大的监狱单间
All she collected was a three-to-ten stretch in Tehachapi.
也许她觉得值得
Perhaps it was worth it to her.
看你能不能拿到客厅
See if you can carry that as far as the living room.
这地方不错，谁替你收拾？
It's nice here, Walter. Who takes care of it for you?
一个黑人妇女每周来打扫两次
A colored woman comes in a couple of times a week.
-自己做早饭吗？    -有时榨点橙汁
Cook your own breakfast? Squeeze a grapefruit once in a while.
-其余的在街角杂货店买    -听起来不错
Get the rest down at the corner drugstore. Sounds wonderful.
周围仅有陌生人
Just strangers beside you.
你不认识他们 就不会恨他们
You don't know them and you don't hate them.
你不用早上坐在餐桌...
You don't have to sit across the table...
向着他和他女儿微笑...
and smile at him and
日复一日的
that daughter of his every morning of your life.
什么女儿？ 钢琴上的女孩？
What daughter? You mean the little girl on the piano?
萝拉，她跟我们同住
Lola. She lives with us.
他替她想的更多
He thinks a lot more of her than he does of me.
-你想过离婚吗？    -他不会同意离婚
You ever think of a divorce? He wouldn't give me a divorce.
我猜是因为他得付笔钱
I suppose because it'd cost him too much money.
他没什么钱，自从做油田生意以来
He hasn't got any money. Not since he went into the oil business.
但你嫁给他时他很有钱？
But he had when you married him?
是的。而我只想要一个家，不行吗？
Yes, he had. And I wanted a home. Why not?
但那不是唯一原因。我是他老婆的看护
But that's not the only reason. I was his wife's nurse.
她长期卧病
She was sick a long time.
她死去时，他非常绝望
When she died, he was terribly broken up.
-我同情他      -现在却恨他
I pitied him so. And now you hate him.
是的，沃特，他对我很刻薄
Yes, Walter. He's so mean to me.
每次我买件衣服买双鞋
Every time I buy a dress or a pair of shoes
他喉咙都得吼破
he yells his head off.
他哪儿也不让我去，不让我说话
He never lets me go anywhere. He keeps me shut up.
一直对我很刻薄
He's always been mean to me.
连他的人身保险受益人也是他女儿
Even his life insurance all goes to that daughter of his.
-那个萝拉。   -屁也没给你？
That Lola. Nothing for you at all?
没，因为我对他来说屁都不是
No. And nothing is just what I'm worth to him.
所以你在黑暗中躺着
So you lie awake in the dark
听着他呼噜声，有了念头
and listen to him snore and get ideas.
沃特，我没想杀他，从来没想
Walter, I don't want to kill him. I never did.
就算他喝醉了打我耳光
Not even when he gets drunk and slaps my face.
-只是你有时恨不得他去死    -也许
Only sometimes you wish he was dead. Perhaps I do.
然后你希望那是个意外，
Then you wish it was an accident,
而你手握那份5万元的保单
and you had that policy for $50,000.
-是吗？    -也许
Is that it? Perhaps that, too.
一晚我们开车从派对回家，他又醉了
The other night we drove home from a party. He was drunk again.
他开进车库时，
When we drove into the garage,
就那么坐在那里头倒在方向盘...
he just sat there with his head on the steering wheel...
汽车还没熄火
and the motor still running.
我当时想，若我不熄火，就这么关门走了，
And I thought what it would be like if I didn't switch it off...
把他留在那里，将会如何
just closed the garage doors and left him there.
我来告诉你会如何
I'll tell you what it'd be like.
如果你买了意外险
If you had that accident policy
然后让一氧化碳办事儿
and tried to pull a monoxide job...
我们公司有个叫基斯的
We've got a guy in our office named Keyes.
骗局对他来说
For him a setup like
像传说中的小菜一碟
that'd be just like a slice of rare roast beef.
3分钟内他就知道不是意外
In three minutes he'd know it wasn't an accident.
10分钟内你到了警局审讯室
In 10 minutes you'd be sitting under the hot lights.
半小时内你就在认罪书上签字了
In a half-hour you'd be signing your name to a confession.
但，沃特，我没干啊，也不会干
But, Walter, I didn't do it and I'm not going to do it.
只要牵涉保险公司就不能干
Not if there's an insurance company in the picture, baby.
他们的把戏比一群猴子加起来还多
They know more tricks than a carload of monkeys.
如果牵涉到死人，他们立马吊死你
And if there's a death mixed up in it, you haven't got a prayer.
就像10个一角能换一元一样确定
They'll hang you just as sure as ten dimes will buy a dollar.
而我不想你被吊死，宝贝
And I don't want you to hang, baby.
别再想了，好吗？
Stop thinking about it, will you?
于是我们就坐着，
So we just sat there.
她开始温柔哭泣，如同窗上雨滴
She started crying softly, like the rain on the window,
而我们未发一言
and we didn't say anything.
也许她已经不再想了，但我还在想...
Maybe she had stopped thinking about it, but I hadn't.
我没法不想
I couldn't.
因为这与我多年来的...
Because it all tied up with something
一个想法联系起来
I'd been thinking about for years.
远在我遇到菲莉丝.迪崔克森之前
Since long before I ever ran into Phyllis Dietrichson.
你应该明白，基斯
Because you know how it is, Keyes.
干这行，你总废寝忘食的...
In this business you can't sleep...
去试图识破别人给你的诡计
for trying to figure out all the tricks they could pull on you.
你就像站在轮盘后的庄家
You're like the guy behind the roulette wheel...
盯紧客人，避免他们连场子都骗走
watching the customers to make sure they don't crook the house.
然后突然一夜，你在想
And then one night, you get to thinking
自己如何骗走场子
how you could crook the house yourself.
如何做得精明
And do it smart.
因为轮盘你已尽在掌握
Because you've got that wheel right under your hands.
其中机关一清二楚
You know every notch in it by heart.
你发现你只需一个搭档
And you figure all you need is a plant out front.
一个实施赌局的托
A shill to put down the bet.
而门铃突然响起
And suddenly the doorbell rings...
整个布局来到你的房间里了
and the whole setup is right there in the room with you.
基斯，我不是想为自己推脱
Look, Keyes, I'm not trying to whitewash myself.
我抵抗过，但我猜我抵抗不够坚决
I fought it, only I guess I didn't fight it hard enough.
赌注是5万块，以及一个男人的性命
The stakes were $50,000, but they were the life of a man, too.
一个没得罪过我的人，除了...
A man who'd never done me any dirt, except...
他娶了一个她毫不在乎的女人
he was married to a woman he didn't care anything about.
却是我在乎的
And I did.
你会打给我吗？沃特？
Will you phone me? Walter?
我恨他，我讨厌回去
I hate him. I loathe going back to him.
-你相信我，是吗沃特？    -我当然相信
You believe me, don't you, Walter? Sure I believe you.
我受不了。吊死又有什么可怕？
I can't stand it anymore. What if they did hang me?
他们不会吊死你的，宝贝
They're not going to hang you, baby.
吊死也比这样好
It's better than going on this way.
他们不会吊死你的，因为...
They're not gonna hang you because...
你会下手而我会帮你
you're gonna do it and I'm gonna help you.
-你知道自己在说什么吗？  -我当然知道...
Do you know what you're saying? Sure, I know what I'm saying.
我们会下手，而且要做得漂亮
We're gonna do it and we're gonna do it right.
-而我知道门道    -沃特，你在伤害我
And I'm the guy that knows how. Walter, you're hurting me.
不会有丝毫差错
There's not going to be any slip-up.
毫无破绽，无懈可击
Nothing sloppy. Nothing weak.
完美无暇
It's got to be perfect.
明天打给我，别用家里座机，去电话亭
Call me tomorrow. But not from your house. From a booth.
时刻小心自己举动
And watch your step every single minute.
必须天衣无缝，明白吗？
This has got to be perfect, you understand?
彻头彻尾
Straight down the line.
就是这样，基斯
That was it, Keyes.
机器开始运作，势不可挡
The machinery had started to move and nothing could stop it.
第一步...
The first thing we had to do
设计让他买意外险
was fix him up with that accident policy.
我知道他不肯
I knew he wouldn't buy,
但我只需他在申请表上签名
but all I wanted was his signature on an application.
所以我要让他在不知签的是什么...
So I had to get him to sign without his knowing
的情况下签名
what he was signing.
还另需一个证人
And I wanted another witness
和菲莉丝一起，听见我向他推销
besides Phyllis to hear me give him a sales talk.
我在试着用你的脑袋思考，基斯...
I was trying to think with your brains, Keyes...
因为我得准备好所有答案
because I wanted all the answers ready...
面对你在迪崔克森死后
for all the questions you were gonna spring
提出的所有问题
as soon as Dietrichson was dead.
几天后，我去了他们家
A couple of nights later I went to the house.
一切顺利 ，
Everything looked fine,
但我不喜欢菲莉丝带来的证人
except I didn't like the witness Phyllis had brought in.
是迪崔克森先生的女儿萝拉
It was Dietrichson's daughter, Lola.
情况令我心里有些别扭
And it made me feel a little queer in the belly...
就让她那么坐在房间
to have her sitting right there in the room,
玩着跳棋
playing Chinese checkers...
好像不会发生任何事情
as if nothing were going to happen.
你应该知道，迪崔克森先生
I suppose you realize, Mr. Dietrichson...
由于你不是雇员
that, not being an employee...
你不受州赔偿保险条例保障
you are not covered by the State Compensation Insurance Act.
你保护自己的唯一办法
The only way you can protect yourself is
就是买个人保险
by having a personal policy of your own.
对 ，我都懂
Yeah, I know all about that.
你接下来会说我需要...
The next thing you'll tell me I need...
地震险，雷电险，冰雹险
earthquake insurance and lightning insurance and hail insurance.
如果我们买下所有险种...
If we bought all the insurance they can think up...
就成穷光蛋了，不是吗宝贝？
we'd stay broke paying for it, wouldn't we, honey?
令我们成穷光蛋的是你
What keeps us broke is you going out
一出去就买五顶帽子
and buying five hats at a crack.
在加州用帽子干嘛？
Who needs a hat in California?
一分钱一分货，迪崔克森先生
Dollar for dollar, Mr. Dietrichson...
意外险是价钱最便宜的保险
accident insurance is the cheapest coverage you can buy.
下次谈吧，奈夫先生，我今天很累
Well, maybe some other time, Mr. Neff. I had a tough day.
那好吧
Just as you say.
要不今晚先解决汽车保险的事吧
Suppose we just settle that automobile insurance tonight.
好
Sure.
那件事只需您签名
All we'll need on that is for you to sign
来申请续保
the application for renewal.
菲莉丝，不玩了你不介意吧？
Phyllis, do you mind if we don't finish this game?
-我觉得很无聊     -有别的可做吗？
It bores me stiff. Got something better to do?
是的
Yes, I have.
父亲，我现在走行吗？
Father, is it all right if I run along now?
-去哪里？跟谁？     -只是安妮，去滑旱冰
Run along where? Who with? Just Anne. We're going roller-skating.
-哪个安妮？     -安妮.马修斯
Anne who? Anne Matthews.
不会又是那个尼诺.扎切提吧？
It's not that Nino Zachetti again, is it?
最好别是扎切提
It better not be that Zachetti guy.
如果我抓到你和那...
If I ever catch you with that...
是安妮.马修斯，告诉你了
It's Anne Matthews, I told you.
也告诉你了是滑旱冰
And I also told you we're going roller-skating.
我约了她在
I'm meeting her
维蒙特和富兰克林交界西北角见面
at the corner of Vermont and Franklin, the northwest corner...
如果你有兴趣的话。而我已经晚了
in case you're interested, and I'm late already.
我希望够清楚了。晚安，父亲
I hope that's all quite clear. Good night, Father.
-晚安，菲莉丝         -晚安，迪崔克森小姐
Good night, Phyllis. Good night, Miss Dietrichson.
-对不起，晚安...      -奈夫
I'm sorry. Good night, Mr... Neff.
晚安，奈夫先生
Good night, Mr. Neff.
人小鬼大呀
A great little fighter for her weight.
请你在这里签名，迪崔克森先生
Now, if you'll just sign these, Mr. Dietrichson.
-签什么？    -汽车续保申请
Sign what? The applications for the auto renewals.
您就能在新保单发出前得到保障了
So you'll be covered until the new policies are issued.
-那得何时？    -大约一星期
When will that be? About a week.
那我驾车往北时会得到保障
Just so I'm covered when I drive up north.
-旧金山？      -帕洛阿尔托
San Francisco? Palo Alto.
他是斯坦福毕业，奈夫先生
He was a Stanford man, Mr. Neff.
仍每年出席校友会
And he still goes to his class reunion every year.
那有什么问题？
What's wrong with that?
我不能开心一下吗，哪怕一年才一次？
Can't I have a little fun, even once a year?
斯坦福的足球很厉害
Great football school, Stanford.
-你踢足球吗，迪崔克森先生？     -左卫
Did you play football, Mr. Dietrichson? Left guard.
-几乎入选校队。签哪里？
Almost made the varsity, too. Where do I sign?
那条线
The bottom line.
-两份都签      -签两次？
Both copies, please. Sign twice, huh?
对，一份是业务员的
Yes. One is the agent's copy.
-我自己要存档     -存档，两份，三份，真麻烦
I need it for my files. Files. Duplicates. Triplicates.
谢谢，迪崔克森先生
Thank you, Mr. Dietrichson.
别担心支票
Don't worry about the check,
我改天去你办公室取
I can pick it up at your office some morning.
-要多少钱?    -147.5元
How much you taking me for? $147.50.
我觉得今晚说够了保险的事了，奈夫先生
I think that's enough insurance for one evening, Mr. Neff.
足够了
Plenty.
上来时给我带些苏打水
Bring me some soda when you come up,
菲莉丝。  晚安，奈夫先生
Phyllis. Good night, Mr. Neff.
晚安，迪崔克森先生
Good night, Mr. Dietrichson.
你的帽子在走廊，奈夫先生
I think you left your hat in the hall, Mr. Neff.
晚安，奈夫先生
Good night, Mr. Neff.
-好了吗，沃特？   -好了
All right, Walter? Fine.
-他签了，是不是？    -当然，你亲眼看见
He signed it, didn't he? Sure he signed it. You saw him.
现在听着，去帕洛阿尔托的事，他何时出发？
Now, listen. That trip to Palo Alto. When does he leave?
月底
End of the month.
-开车去？     -一向都是
He drives, huh? He always drives.
这次不行，你要让他坐火车
Not this time. You're gonna make him take the train.
-为什么？     -因为坐火车会更完美
Why? Because it's all worked out for a train.
听着宝贝，每桩意外险都会有个条款...
Listen, baby. There's a clause in every accident policy...
叫做双倍赔偿
a little thing called double indemnity.
算是保险公司给顾客
The insurance companies put it in
的额外优惠
as a sort of come-on for the customers.
意思是他们在特定事故时会付双倍
That means they pay double on certain accidents.
那种几乎不会发生的事故
The kind that almost never happen.
比如说，顾客在火车上死亡
Like for instance, if a guy is killed on the train...
他们就会付10万而不是5万
they pay $100,000 instead of $50,000.
-我明白了   -我们要做到极限
I see. We're hitting it for the limit, baby.
所以必须是火车
That's why it's got to be the train.
他会坐火车的，沃特，就像你需要的
It'll be the train, Walter. Just the way you want it.
彻头彻尾
Straight down the line.
嗨，奈夫先生
Hello, Mr. Neff.
是我
It's me.
-有什么事？    -我在等你
Is anything wrong? I've been waiting for you.
等我？为什么？
For me? Why?
我想让你捎我一段，如果顺路
I thought you could let me ride with you, if you're going my way.
-你走哪条路？    -下山，去维蒙特
Which way would that be? Down the hill. Down Vermont.
当然，维蒙特街与富兰克林街西北角，是吗？
Sure. Vermont and Franklin. Northwest corner, wasn't it?
没问题，迪崔克森小姐
Be glad to, Miss Dietrichson.
去溜冰？
Going roller-skating, huh?
-你喜欢溜冰？   -溜不溜都行
You like roller-skating? I can take it or leave it.
-但今晚不会溜？    -是的
Only tonight you're leaving it? Yes, I am.
我在家里很难熬
I'm having a very tough time at home.
我爸不懂我，菲莉丝恨我
My father doesn't understand me and Phyllis hates me.
-听起来真糟      -所以我得偶尔撒谎
Sounds tough, all right. That's why I have to lie sometimes.
你是说不去维蒙特街与富兰克林街 ？
You mean it's not Vermont and Franklin?
地点倒是真的
It's Vermont and Franklin all right.
但不是安妮.马修斯，而是尼诺.扎切提
Only it's not Anne Matthews. It's Nino Zachetti.
你不会告发我，对吧？
You won't tell on me, will you?
-我要考虑一下     -尼诺不是我爸说的那么差
I'd have to think it over. Nino's not what my father says at all.
他只是运气差，他在南加州大学读医科
He's just had bad luck. He was doing premed at USC...
晚上在剧院做引座员
and working nights as an usher in a theater downtown.
因为学分不足而被退学
Got behind in his credits, flunked out.
然后与上司顶嘴被解雇，他太鲁莽
Then he lost his job for talking back. He's so hot-headed.
代价真大，不是吗？
Becomes expensive, doesn't it?
我爸大概认为没人配得上他女儿
Guess my father thinks nobody's good enough for his daughter...
除了标准石油公司老板
except maybe the guy that owns Standard Oil.
我希望他理解我，我不能放弃尼诺
I wish he'd see it my way. I can't give Nino up.
船到桥头自然直，迪崔克森小姐
It'll all straighten out, Miss Dietrichson.
我想会吧
I suppose it will sometime.
就是这里，奈夫先生
This is the corner right here, Mr. Neff.
尼诺？过来，尼诺
Nino? Over here, Nino.
-这是奈夫先生，尼诺...     -你好，尼诺
This is Mr. Neff, Nino. Hello, Nino.
我大名扎切提
The name is Zachetti.
尼诺，别这样，奈夫先生送我来的
Nino, please. Mr. Neff gave me a ride from the house.
我告诉了他我们的事
I told him all about us.
何必要告诉他？
Why does he have to get told about us?
不用担心奈夫先生
We don't have to worry about Mr. Neff, Nino.
我不是担心
I'm not doing any worrying.
只是别四处张扬
Just don't you broadcast so much.
你怎么回事，尼诺？
Well, what's the matter with you, Nino?
-他是朋友     -我没有朋友
Why, he's a friend. I don't have any friends.
就算有，我喜欢自己选择
If I did, I like to pick them myself. Come on.
听着，她要搭车，我就捎她一段而已
Look, sonny, she needed a ride, so I brought her along.
有什么不好吗？
Is that anything to get tough about?
好了，萝拉，决定吧，你来不来？
All right, Lola, make up your mind. Are you coming or aren't you?
当然来
Of course I'm coming.
别介意他，奈夫先生，谢谢载我一程
Don't mind him, Mr. Neff. And thanks a lot for the ride.
你真好。  尼诺？
You're awfully sweet. Nino?
她是个好女孩
She was a nice kid.
他可能也比表面上好一些
Maybe he was a little better than he sounded.
但当时
But right then
想起我身后的公文包...
it gave me a nasty feeling to be thinking about them at all...
和里面她父亲的签名...
with that briefcase right behind my head
以及签名的含义时
that had her father's signature in it...
我浑身不自在
and what that signature meant.
签名的含义是他离死不远了
It meant he was a dead pigeon.
那只是时间问题，而且时间不长了
It was only a question of time, and not very much time at that.
知道洛斯菲利兹的大市场吗，基斯？
You know that big market up on Los Feliz, Keyes?
那是菲莉丝和我挑选的碰头处
That's the place Phyllis and I had picked for a meeting place.
我脑中计划已经成型
I already had most of the plan in my head...
但好多细节仍需理清
but a lot of details had to be worked out.
而日子到时她必须了然于心
And she had to know them all by heart when the time came.
从今我们必须小心翼翼
We had to be very careful from now on.
不能让人看见我们一起
We couldn't let anybody see us together.
连通电话也不行
We couldn't even talk to each other on the telephone.
至少不能用双方座机
Not from her house or at my office, anyway.
所以她每天上午11点去市场
So she was to be in the market every morning about 11:00,
买些东西
buying stuff.
而我需要时可以在那里碰到她
And I could sort of run into her there any day I wanted to.
装作偶然
Sort of accidentally on purpose.
-沃特，我想...      -别那么大声
Walter, I wanted to... Not so loud.
我从昨天起就想和你谈谈
I wanted to talk to you, ever since yesterday.
-让我先说，事情已搞定
Let me talk first. It's all set.
意外险批下来了，保单在我口袋里
The accident policy came through. I've got it in my pocket.
支票我也拿到，我在油田见过他
I got his check, too. I saw him down in the oil fields.
他以为支付的是汽车保险
He thought he was paying for the auto insurance.
支票抬头只写了保险公司
The check's just made out to the company,
所以支付什么都行
so it could be for anything.
但你得寄出一张汽车保险支票，明白吗？
But you have to send a check for the auto insurance, see?
那就没问题了
It'll be all right that way,
因为其中一辆车在你的名下
because one of the cars is in your name.
打开包，快点
Open your bag. Quick.
你能打开保险箱吗？
Can you get in the safe-deposit box?
-能，我俩都有钥匙     -好
Yes. We both have keys. Fine.
但先别放保单进去，我再告诉你时间
But don't put the policy in there yet. I'll tell you when.
记住，你从没见过它，更没碰过它
Remember, you never saw it, you never even touched it,
明白吗？
you understand?
-我不是傻瓜      -好的，他何时搭火车？
I'm not a fool. Okay. When is he leaving on the train?
-问题就在这，他不去了     -什么？
That's just it. He isn't going. What?
我一直想说的就是这事，行程取消了
That's what I've been trying to tell you. The trip is off.
发生什么事？
What happened?
先生，可以帮我拿那包婴儿食品吗？
Mister, could you reach me that package of baby food?
上面那一包？
That one up there?
真不懂干吗老把我需要的放顶层
I don't know why they always put what I want on the top shelf.
继续说，我在听
Go ahead. I'm listening.
他从油井掉下，腿断了，打了石膏
He had a fall-down at the well. Broke his leg. It's in a cast.
-腿断了？     -现在怎么办，沃特？
Broke his leg? What do we do now, Walter?
-只有等了     -等什么？
Nothing. We just wait. Wait for what?
等他能搭火车
Until he can take the train.
我说过必须是火车
I told you it's got to be the train.
但我们不能等， 我受不了了
But we can't wait. I can't go on like this.
听着，我们不能只图快
Look, we're not gonna grab a hammer
不能拿个锤子就把他砸死
and do it quick, just to get it over with.
-还有其他办法    -我们不用其他方法
There are other ways. We're not gonna do it other ways.
但我们不能就此拉倒
But we can't leave it like this.
如果他发现意外险的事
What do you suppose would happen
你觉得会发生什么？
if he found out about the accident policy?
很多事，但比站在死刑场上好
Plenty. But not as bad as sitting in that death house.
别这么说话
Don't ever talk like that.
别就此失去理智，就这样
Don't let's start losing our heads, that's all.
不是理智，我们在失去勇气
It's not our heads. It's our nerve we're losing.
借过
Excuse me.
我们一定要做的完美，我一直在说
We're gonna do it right. That's all I said.
是等待让我难过
It's the waiting that's getting me.
我也一样难过，宝贝
It's getting me just as bad, baby.
-但我们一定得等     -也许是，但，沃特...
But we've got to wait. Maybe we have, Walter, only...
没有你日子很难过，好像我们之间有一道墙
it's so tough without you. It's like a wall between us.
我得走了，宝贝。我无时无刻不想念你
I better go, baby. I'm thinking of you every minute.
那之后整整一周，我再没见她
After that, a full week went by and I didn't see her once.
我试着忘记她，和整个计划
I tried to keep my mind off her and off the whole idea.
我不断告诉自己
I kept telling myself
是我的所谓宿命
that maybe those Fates they say watch over you...
弄断了他的腿，给我一条出路
had gotten together and broken his leg to give me a way out.
那天是6月15日，你或者记得，基斯
Then it was the 15th of June. You may remember that date, Keyes.
你下午3点左右来我的办公室
You came into my office around 3:00 in the afternoon.
嗨，基斯
Hello, Keyes.
我刚从诺顿办公室回来
I just came from Norton's office.
半年度营业报告公布了
The semiannual sales records are out.
你是最佳销售员，沃特
You're high man, Walter.
连续第二次了，恭喜
That's twice in a row. Congratulations.
-谢谢    有兴趣喝一杯吗？
Thanks. How would you like a cheap drink?
有兴趣减薪50元吗?
How would you like a $50 cut in salary?
-我应该现在就笑还是等等？   -我说真的
Do I laugh now or wait till it gets funny? No, I'm serious.
我刚跟诺顿谈过
I've just been talking to Norton.
我的文件堆积如山
Too much stuff piling up on my desk.
工作压力太大
Too much pressure on my nerves.
半晚上在辗转反侧
I spend half the night walking up and down in my bed.
我得有个助手，于是想到你
I've got to have an assistant and I thought of you.
我？为什么找我？
Me? Why pick on me?
那，我有个离奇的想法，觉得你很合适
Well, because I've got a crazy idea you might be good at the job.
是很离奇，我是个销售员
That's crazy, all right. I'm a salesman.
对 ，你长袖善舞 ，能文能武
Yeah. A peddler, a gladhander, a backslapper.
做销售员实在太浪费
You're too good to be a salesman.
没人做销售员会浪费
Nobody's too good to be a salesman. Phooey!
你们的工作就是按门铃
All you guys do is just ring doorbells
说一番机械套话
and dish out a smooth line of monkey talk.
你是介意降薪50，是吗？
What's troubling you is that $50 cut, isn't it?
-谁都会介意     -听着，沃特
Well, that'd trouble anybody. Now look, Walter.
我说的工作需要头脑与正义感
The job I'm talking about takes brains and integrity.
和比50个销售员加起来还多的胆量
It takes more guts than there is in 50 salesmen.
这是保险业中的热门
It's the hottest job in the business.
对，但还是个办公室工作
Yeah, but it's still a desk job.
-我不想被困在办公室     -办公室工作？
I don't want to be nailed to a desk. Desk job?
你就看到这些？
Is that all you can see in it?
只有朝九晚五放你屁股的破椅子？
Just a hard chair to park your pants on from 9:00 to 5:00, huh?
只有大堆文件...
Just a pile of papers to shuffle around,
几根铅笔...
and five sharp pencils...
算数的黑板...
and a scratch pad to make figures on,
胡乱的涂鸦
maybe a little doodling on the side.
但，我不是这么看的，沃特
Well, that's not the way I look at it, Walter.
我说，索赔员是外科医生
To me, a claims man is a surgeon,
办公桌是手术台
that desk is an operating table...
铅笔是手术刀和骨锯
and those pencils are scalpels and bone chisels.
那些纸不只是
And those papers are not just
赔偿声明、表格和数据
forms and statistics and claims for compensation.
他们是活生生的，充满戏剧性
They're alive. They're packed with drama...
充满纠结的希望和扭曲的梦想
with twisted hopes and crooked dreams.
索赔员，沃特，是医生、侦探和...
A claims man, Walter, is a doctor and a bloodhound and a...
谁？好，等一下
Who? Okay, hold on a minute.
索赔员是医生
A claims man is a doctor
侦探、警察、法官、陪审团
and a bloodhound and a cop and a judge and a jury...
和告解神父，集于一身
and a father confessor, all in one.
而你想告诉我你没兴趣？
And you want to tell me you're not interested?
你不想用脑袋工作？
You don't want to work with your brains?
你只想用手按门铃来工作？
All you want to work is with your finger on the doorbell...
就为一周多几块钱？   有个女人找你
for a few bucks more a week. There's a dame on your phone.
-我是沃特.奈夫     -我必须打给你，沃特
Walter Neff speaking. I had to call you, Walter.
事关紧急，有人在旁边吗？
It's very urgent. Are you with somebody?
是，我是。我再打给你好吗，麦姬 ？
Yes, I am. Can't I call you back, Margie?
不行，我没时间，很紧急
No, you can't. I've only got a minute. It can't wait.
听着，他今晚出发，坐火车，你在听吗？
Listen. He's going tonight. On the train. Are you listening?
-沃特？     -我在听，麦姬
Walter? Yeah. I'm listening, Margie.
-有话快说好吗？    -他拄拐杖
Only, make it snappy, will you? He's on crutches.
医生说
The doctor says
如果小心点他能去，活动对他有好处
he can go if he's careful. The change will do him good.
太好了，沃特，如你所愿，坐火车
It's wonderful, Walter. Just the way you wanted it, on a train.
而且拄拐杖会更有利，是吗？
Only with the crutches it makes it much better, doesn't it?
对，好多了
Yeah. Yeah, that's 100% better.
稍等一下好吗？
Hold the line a minute, will you?
基斯，等会我去找你？
Keyes, suppose I join you in your office?
没关系，我等你
That's all right. I'll wait.
只是告诉她别说上一天
Only tell her not to take all day.
继续
Go ahead.
是格伦戴尔10点15分的火车，我开车送他
It's the 10:15 from Glendale. I'm driving him.
还是那条黑暗的街道，是吗？
It's still the same dark street, isn't it?
-信号是三声喇叭     -好，还有事吗？
And the signal is three honks on the horn. Okay. Anything else?
没有
No.
哦...
Oh, uh...
你选了什么颜色？
what color did you pick?
蓝色，海军蓝。 他左腿打石膏
Blue. Navy blue. And the cast is on his left leg.
恩
Mmm-hmm.
好，很适合我
Yeah, that suits me fine.
事到临头了，沃特，我浑身发抖
This is it, Walter. I'm shaking like a leaf.
但我们会彻头彻尾
But it's straight down the line for both of us.
-我爱你，沃特。   -再见
I love you, Walter. Goodbye.
-对不起，基斯      -怎么了？
Sorry, Keyes. What's the matter?
有女孩追你吗？有新欢？还是说与我无关？
Dames chasing you again? Or still? Or is it none of my business?
如果我告诉你是个客人...
If I told you it was a customer...
麦姬，我猜她喝酒对瓶吹
Margie. I bet she drinks from the bottle.
你为什么不安定下来结婚，沃特？
Why don't you settle down and get married, Walter?
-你为什么不呢？      -我曾经差点，很久以前
Why don't you, for instance? I almost did, once. Long time ago.
基斯，我得打电话给客人
Now look, Keyes, I've got to call on a prospect.
我俩连教堂都选好了
Even had the church picked out, the dame and I.
她有一件带荷叶边的丝裙
She had a white satin dress with flounces on it.
我正在去珠宝店买戒指的路上
I was on my way to the jewelry store to buy the ring.
然后这里突然有个小人开始活动
And then suddenly that little man in here started working on me.
所以你回去把她调查一番？
So you went back and had her investigated?
对，事情终于水落石出
Yeah. And the stuff that came out...
她自从16岁就开始染发
She'd been dyeing her hair ever since she was 16.
她家有个躁郁症患者，她母亲那边
There was a manic depressive in her family, on her mother's side.
她已经有个丈夫
She already had one husband.
他是巴尔的摩的职业台球手...
He was a professional pool player in Baltimore.
-至于她哥...       -我大致明白了
And as for her brother... I get the general idea.
她是众多骗子中的一个
She was a tramp from a long line of tramps.
对，好了，好了
Yeah. All right, all right.
-那我怎么对诺顿说？关于我说的那份工作？
Now what do I say to Norton? What about this job I want you for?
我想我不想要，基斯
I don't think I want it, Keyes.
-但非常感谢      -好吧
Thanks just the same. Fair enough.
你得明白，我选择你，
Only get this, I picked you for the job...
不是认为你很聪明
not because I think you're so darn smart...
而是因为我以为你没有...
but because I thought you were a shade less dumb
表面看起来那么笨
than the rest of the outfit.
大概我错了。 你并不聪明，沃特
Guess I was wrong. You're not smarter, Walter.
只是比较高
You're just a little taller.
是的，基斯
Yes, Keyes.
我说到的宿命只是拖延了我
Those Fates I was talking about had only been stalling me off.
现在它已启动开关，运转齿轮
Now they had thrown the switch. The gears had meshed.
用来思考的时间已用尽
The time for thinking had all run out.
我希望从始至终
I wanted my movements accounted
我的行动都无懈可击
for up to the last possible moment.
所以我离开办公室时
So when I left the office
把计算本放到办公桌上，假装遗落
I put my rate book on the desk as if I had forgotten it.
那是我的伏笔之一
That was part of my alibi.
从此开始，只需按照时间表...
From here on, it was a question of following the timetable...
按部就班
move by move.
我大约7点到家，停车入库
I got home about 7:00 and drove right into the garage.
这又是制造不在场证明的伏笔
This was another item to establish my alibi.
-嗨，奈夫先生     -你好，查理
Hi, Mr. Neff. Hello, Charlie.
帮我洗车好吗？
How about giving the heap a wash job?
你何时要？
How soon you gonna want it?
前面有几辆了
I got a couple cars ahead of you.
随你方便，查理
Any time you get to it, Charlie.
-晚上我待在家     -好
I'm staying in tonight. Okay.
回公寓后我打给路.舒华兹...
Up in my apartment I called Lou Schwartz...
我办公室的另一销售员
one of the salesmen that shared my office.
他住在威斯伍德
He lived in Westwood,
所以那算长途电话，会有记录
so it was a toll call and there'd be a record of it.
我告诉他我忘带计算本，我需要...
I told him I'd forgotten my rate book and needed some dope...
一些我在弄的公债事务的资料...
on the public liability bond I was figuring.
我换上...
I changed into
迪崔克森将会穿的海军蓝衣服
a navy blue suit like Dietrichson was going to wear.
路.舒华兹回电，给了我很多数据
Lou Schwartz called me back and gave me a lot of figures.
我将毛巾，胶带装进衣兜
I stuffed a hand towel and a roll of adhesive into my pockets...
可以用来做成...
so I could fake something
像断腿上石膏的东西
that looked like a cast on a broken leg.
接着，我在电话里插了张卡片
Next, I stuck a card inside the telephone box...
如果铃响，卡片就会掉
so that it would fall down if the bell rang.
那样我就知道我不在时是否有来电
That way I'd know if anybody had called me while I was away.
门铃也如法炮制
Then I did the same thing to the doorbell
以防有人上门找我
in case anybody came to see me.
我走保洁楼梯离开住所，没人看见我
I left the apartment by the service stairs. Nobody saw me.
我步行从公寓走到迪崔克森家
I walked all the way from my apartment to the Dietrichson house.
我不想搭巴士
I didn't want to take the bus...
因为有可能...
because there was always the chance
有人会记得在巴士上见过我
that someone might remember seeing me on it.
我谨慎到这种程度
I was being that careful.
我又问到金银花的味道
I could smell that honeysuckle again.
只是这次更加强烈，而这次是晚上
Only it was even stronger, now that it was night.
我尽可能安静的打开车库门
I slid the garage door open as quietly as I could.
她已按我说的，将车头朝外停好
She'd backed the sedan in, just the way I told her to.
我认为这样停更安全
I'd figured it was safer that way...
以防他在她将车开出前就上车
in case he got into the car before she drove it out.
我进到车后部
I got into the back of the car.
躺在地上等待
I lay there on the floor and waited.
我一直在想着...
All the time I was thinking about
通往火车站的黑暗街道
that dark street on the way to the station...
我的动手之处...
where I was to do it...
以及作为信号的三声喇叭
and the three honks on the horn that were to be the signal.
十分钟后，他们下来了
About 10 minutes later they came down.
-还好吗，亲爱的？    -是的，还好
All right, honey? Yeah, I'm all right.
我马上把车开出来
I'll have the car out in a second.
-慢慢来，还有很多时间     -对
Take it easy, honey. We've got lots of time. Yeah.
牢记医生的话。如果你不小心...
Remember what the doctor said. If you get careless...
以后会成为长短腿
you might end up with a shorter leg.
那又怎样？我可以打断另一条让它们一样长
So what? I could break the other one and match them up again.
摆脱我让你感觉不错，是吗？
It makes you feel pretty good to get away from me, doesn't it?
只是四天，最迟周一我就回来
It's only for four days. I'll be back Monday at the latest.
不是这条街，干嘛在这转弯？
This is not the right street. Why did you turn here?
你这是干吗？
What are you doing that for?
按喇叭干吗？
What are you honking the horn for?
你应付搬运工和售票员
You take care of the redcap and the conductor.
-不用担心      -尽量离我远点
Don't worry. Keep away from me as much as you can.
告诉他们我不想被帮助
Tell them I don't want to be helped.
我说过，不用担心，沃特
I said, don't worry, Walter.
火车一走你就出发，
You start as soon as the train leaves.
到达冶炼厂后，
When you get to the refinery,
离开公路开上土路
turn off the highway onto the dirt road.
从那开始整五分之四英里...
From there it's exactly eight-tenths of a mile...
就到铁轨旁的垃圾场。记住
to the dump beside the tracks. Remember.
-我全都记得。    -不要超速
I remember everything. No speeding.
你不想被警察截停，而他在后面
You don't want any cops stopping you with him in the back.
沃特，我们排练过很多次了。
Walter, we've been through all that so many times.
离开公路时，关闭所有灯光
When you leave the highway, turn off all your lights.
我会到后面的观景台
I'll be back on the observation platform.
我会在预定位置附近跳车
I'll drop off as close to the spot as I can.
等火车经过后，闪两次灯
Let the train pass, then dim your lights twice.
-旧金山，女士？    -9车厢，11室
San Francisco train, lady? Car 9, section 11.
只有我丈夫
Just my husband.
9车厢，11室？这边请
Car 9, section 11? This way please.
谢谢。我丈夫不希望别人帮忙
Thank you. My husband doesn't like to be helped.
8车厢。在那里
Car number 8. Up there.
9车厢，11室。 谢谢
Car 9, section 11. Thank you.
这是车票，一定要小心腿
Here're the tickets. Take good care of yourself with that leg.
好，你开车回家要小心
Yeah. You take it easy driving home.
-我会想你的，宝贝    -11室，先生
I'll miss you, honey. Section 11, sir.
-全部登车！    -谢谢
All aboard! Thank you.
-再见，亲爱的      -全部登车！
Goodbye, honey. All aboard!
好运，亲爱的
Good luck, honey.
服务员，帮我弄好铺位好吗？
Porter, will you make up my berth right away?
是，先生
Yes, sir.
我去后面观景台抽一口烟
I'm going back to the observation car for a smoke.
这边，先生
Right this way, sir.
要椅子吗？
Like a chair?
不，谢谢，我想站一下
No, thanks. I'd rather stand.
-你去很远吗？     -帕洛阿尔托
You going far? Palo Alto.
我叫杰克逊
My name's Jackson.
我要一路去梅德福，俄勒岗州梅德福
I'm going all the way to Medford. Medford, Oregon.
我曾断过胳膊
I had a broken arm once.
石膏令人奇痒难忍，是不是？
That darn cast itches something fierce, doesn't it?
我的让我快疯了
I thought I'd go crazy with mine.
帕尔阿尔托是个不错的小镇，你是斯坦福的？
Palo Alto's a nice little town. You a Stanford man?
-我以前是    -我猜你落下东西了
I used to be. I'll bet you left something behind.
我经常如此
I always do.
我的雪茄盒
My cigar case.
可能落在我车厢里的外衣里
I guess I left it in my overcoat back in the section.
你想自己卷支烟吗，未请教...
Would you care to roll yourself a cigarette, Mister...
迪崔克森
Dietrichson.
不，谢谢，我想抽雪茄
No thanks, I really prefer a cigar.
也许服务员可以...，好吧，我可以给你拿来
Maybe the porter could... Well, I could get your cigars for you.
-很乐意，迪崔克森先生     -希望不会麻烦到你
Be glad to, Mr. Dietrichson. If it's not too much trouble.
-9车厢，11室    -9车厢，11室
Car 9, section 11. Car 9, section 11.
乐意效劳
With pleasure.
好了， 必须快点
Okay. This has gotta be fast.
这儿，拿着他的帽子，去前边铁轨拾回拐杖
Here, take his hat. Pick up the crutches back on the tracks.
好了，宝贝。 行了
Okay, baby. That's it.
好的，走吧
All right. Let's go.
回去路上，我们又排练一次...
On the way back, we went over once more...
审讯时她该如何表现...
what she was to do at the inquest...
如果有审讯的话，以及保险的事，肯定会提及
if they had one, and about the insurance, when that came up.
我曾担心她可能会有些崩溃，
I was afraid she might go to pieces a little,
在我们行事完毕后
now that we had done it.
但她表现完美，毫不紧张
But she was perfect. No nerves.
没一滴泪，甚至眼都没眨
Not a tear, not even a blink of the eyes.
她在离我公寓一个街区外放下我
She dropped me a block from my apartment house.
沃特，怎么了？你不打算吻我吗？
Walter, what's the matter? Aren't you going to kiss me?
彻头彻尾，不是吗？
It's straight down the line, isn't it?
-我爱你，沃特     -我爱你，宝贝
I love you, Walter. I love you, baby.
11点2分了
It was two minutes past 11:00,
我又从保洁楼梯上楼
as I went up the service stairs again.
这次也没人看见我
Nobody saw me this time either.
我检查了门铃、电话
In the apartment I checked the bells.
卡片没动，没人来电，没人上门
The cards hadn't moved. No calls. No visitors.
然后我又换了衣服
Then I changed my clothes again.
还剩最后一件事
That left one last thing to do.
我得下去车房。我想让查理再看到我。
I had to go down to the garage. I wanted Charlie to see me again.
你又要用车吗？我还没洗好
You gonna use your car, after all? I'm not quite through.
没关系，查理
Well, that's all right, Charlie.
只是去杂货店买点吃的
Just going up to the drugstore to get something to eat.
工作了一整夜
Been working upstairs all night.
肚子有点抗议啊
My stomach's getting a little sore at me.
是的，先生
Yes, sir, Mr. Neff.
事情终于告一段落
That was all there was to it.
没有错误，没有疏漏
Nothing had slipped, nothing had been overlooked.
没什么能暴露我们
There was nothing to give us away.
然而，基斯
And yet, Keyes,
当我走向杂货店时...
as I was walking down the street to the drugstore...
我突然觉得一切都将坍塌
suddenly it came over me that everything would go wrong.
听来很疯狂，但这是真的，帮帮我
It sounds crazy, Keyes, but it's true, so help me.
我听不见自己的脚步声
I couldn't hear my own footsteps.
因为那是死人的脚步
It was the walk of a dead man.
那是我毕生最漫长的一夜
That was the longest night I ever lived through, Keyes...
接下来一天更难熬
and the next day was worse,
因事情已经上报纸
when the story had broke in the papers...
公司的人开始讨论这事
and they started talking about it at the office...
那天之后，你开始接手
and the day after that, when you started digging into it.
我将手放进衣兜
I kept my hands in my pockets
因为我觉得它们颤抖不已
because I thought they were shaking.
我带上墨镜，不让人看我眼睛
I put on dark glasses so people couldn't see my eyes.
然后又摘下来
And then I took them off again
以免他们觉得奇怪
so they wouldn't get to wondering why I wore them.
我尝试保持冷静，但是...
I tried to hold myself together, but...
又感觉我的紧张将我撕裂
I could feel my nerves pulling me to pieces.
-噢，沃特？     -嗨，基斯
Oh, Walter? Hello, Keyes.
过来，大老板想见我们
Come along. The big boss wants to see us.
-迪崔克森的案子？    -一定是
The Dietrichson case? Must be.
-有问题吗？     -他死了
Anything wrong? Well, the guy is dead.
我们保的险，我们要赔大了
We had him insured and it's gonna cost us dough.
这一直是问题
That's always wrong.
-他们掌握什么情况了？    -验尸报告
What have they got so far? Autopsy report.
没有心脏病，没中风
No heart failure, no apoplexy,
或任何疾病原因
no predisposing medical cause of any kind.
死于脖子断了
Died of a broken neck.
-几时审讯？      -早晨审过了
When's the inquest? Had it this morning.
他的妻女认尸完毕
His wife and daughter made the identification.
火车职员
The train people
及一些乘客说...
and some of the passengers told how he went through...
他走到了观景台
to the observation car.
45分钟内就结束了    裁决呢？   意外死亡
It was all over in 45 minutes. Verdict? Accidental death.
警方认为呢？
What do the police figure?
认为他被拐杖绊倒，摔下火车
That he got tangled up in his crutches and fell off the train.
觉得事实如此
They're satisfied.
又不是他们赔钱。来吧，沃特
It's not their dough. Come on, Walter.
好。   非常感谢，各位
All right. Thank you very much, gentlemen.
我相信法律立场已经很清晰了
I believe the legal position is now clear.
请待命，我也许需要你们
Please stand by. I may need you later.
请进，基斯先生，还有你，奈夫先生
Come in, Mr. Keyes. You, too, Mr. Neff.
你觉得今天暖和的不舒服吗，基斯先生？
You find this an uncomfortably warm day, Mr. Keyes?
抱歉，诺顿先生，我不知道这是正式会议
I'm sorry, Mr. Norton, but I didn't know this was formal.
-两位请坐    -谢谢
Sit down, gentlemen. Thank you.
有新进展吗？
Any new developments?
我刚打长途电话给杰克逊
I just talked to this Jackson long distance,
在俄勒冈，梅德福
up in Medford, Oregon.
那是谁？
Who's Jackson?
他是最后看见迪崔克森活着的人
He's the last man who saw Dietrichson alive.
他们一起在观景台，聊天
They were out on the observation platform together, talking.
迪崔克森想抽雪茄，于是杰克逊回去...
Dietrichson wanted a cigar and so Jackson went back...
帮迪崔克森拿雪茄盒
to get Dietrichson's cigar case for him.
他返回观景台时，迪崔克森没了
When he returned to the observation platform, no Dietrichson.
杰克逊当时没觉得有什么不对
Well, Jackson didn't think anything was wrong until...
直到电报在圣巴巴拉送至火车
a wire caught up with the train at Santa Barbara.
他们在伯班克附近的铁轨旁发现迪崔克森的尸体
They found Dietrichson's body on the tracks near Burbank.
雪茄盒的事很有趣
Very interesting about the cigar case.
-还有别的吗？     -没什么了
Anything else? No, not much.
迪崔克森的秘书说
Dietrichson's secretary says
她不知道保险的事
she didn't know anything about the policy.
还有女儿
There's a daughter,
但她只记得奈夫和她父亲...
but all she remembers is Neff talking to her father...
有一晚在他们家中谈过意外险
about accident insurance at their house one night.
我起初说服不了他
I couldn't sell him at first.
迪崔克森拒绝了，他说他再考虑
Mr. Dietrichson opposed it. He said he'd think it over.
后来我在油田见他时把他搞定了
Later I saw him in the oil fields and closed him.
他签了申请表，给了我支票
He signed the application and gave me his check.
这单买卖干的不错啊，奈夫先生
A fine piece of salesmanship that was, Mr. Neff.
得了，没必要责怪奈夫
Well, there's no sense in pushing Neff around.
他在全公司销售业绩最好
He's got the best sales record in the office.
难道销售员还得预料到顾客...
Are your salesmen supposed to know a customer
会摔下火车吗？
is going to fall off the train?
摔下火车？你肯定迪崔克森是摔下火车吗 ？
Fall off a train? Are we sure Dietrichson fell off the train?
-我没听懂    -没听懂，基斯先生？
I don't get it. You don't, Mr. Keyes?
那你对案子怎么看？
Then what do you think of this case?
这份保单将会让我们赔一大笔
This policy might cost us a great deal of money.
你知道，它包含双倍赔偿条文
As you know, it contains a double indemnity clause.
你有什么观点？
Just what is your opinion?
-没有任何观点。    -没有任何预感？
No opinion at all. Not even a hunch?
你那些有趣的预感之一？
One of those interesting little hunches of yours?
没有，无任何预感
Nope. Not even a hunch.
我很意外，基斯先生。我形成了一个很确定的观点。
I'm surprised, Mr. Keyes. I've formed a very definite opinion.
我觉得我知道。事实上，
I think I know. In fact,
我确定我知道迪崔克森发生了什么事
I know I know what happened to Dietrichson.
-你确定你知道什么？     -我知道这不是意外
You know you know what? I know it was not an accident.
-你有什么看法？      -我？
What do you say to that? Me?
对，球到你手了，看看你的表现
Well, you've got the ball. Let's see you run with it.
有种普遍的看法...
There's a widespread feeling
就因为一个人有间大办公室...
that just because a man has a large office...
是吗？请叫她进来
Yes? Have her come in, please.
有种普遍的看法...
There's a widespread feeling that...
就因为一个人有间大办公室，他就肯定是白痴
just because a man has a large office, he must be an idiot.
我有访客，希望你们别介意
I'm having a visitor, if you don't mind.
不，不，我想你们留下看我处理
No, no. I want you to stay and watch me handle this.
迪崔克森太太
Mrs. Dietrichson.
非常感谢你能来，迪崔克森太太
Thank you very much for coming, Mrs. Dietrichson.
请相信我很感激。这位是基斯先生
I assure you I appreciate it. This is Mr. Keyes.
-你好      -你好
How do you do? How do you do?
-还有奈夫先生    -我见过奈夫先生，你好
And Mr. Neff. I've met Mr. Neff. How do you do?
迪崔克森太太，请坐好吗？
Mrs. Dietrichson. Won't you sit down?
对您的丧亲之痛我们深感同情
May I extend our sympathy in your bereavement?
我曾犹豫过
I hesitated before
这么快就叫您来是否合适
asking you to come here so soon after your loss.
但既然您来了
But now that you're here
希望您别介意我直入主题？
I hope you won't mind if I plunge straight into business?
你知道我们为何叫你来，是吗？
You know why we asked you to come, don't you?
不，我只知道你的秘书语气很紧急
No. All I know is that your secretary made it sound very urgent.
你丈夫向本公司购买了意外险
Your husband had an accident policy with this company.
很明显你不知道，迪崔克森太太
Evidently you don't know that, Mrs. Dietrichson.
是的，我记得在家讨论过
No. I remember some talk at the house,
但他好像不想买
but he didn't seem to want it.
你丈夫几天后购买了，
Your husband took the policy out a few days later,
迪崔克森太太
Mrs. Dietrichson.
你可能会在他的私人物品中找到保单
You'll probably find the policy among his personal effects.
他的保险箱还没打开
His safe-deposit box hasn't been opened yet.
那好像需要税务审查员在场
It seems a tax examiner has to be present.
对不起，迪崔克森太太，我不想让你觉得...
Please, Mrs. Dietrichson, I don't want you to think...
你在遭受盘问...
you're being subjected to any questioning...
但我们想知道几件事
but there are a few things we should like to know.
哪方面的？
What sort of things?
我们收到验尸官的报告
We have the report of the coroner's inquest.
意外死亡。我们并不完全满意
Accidental death. We are not entirely satisfied.
事实上，我们一点都不满意
In fact, we are not satisfied at all.
坦白说，迪崔克森太太，我们怀疑...
Frankly, Mrs. Dietrichson, we suspect...
他是自杀
a suicide.
-对不起。要杯水吗？    -好
I'm sorry. Would you like a glass of water? Please.
谢谢
Thank you.
你丈夫最近有否情绪低落，喜怒无常，
Had your husband been depressed or moody lately,
迪崔克森太太？
Mrs. Dietrichson?
比如说，他有没有财务问题？
Did he have financial worries, for instance?
他状态很好
He was perfectly all right
我也不知道有什么财政问题
and I don't know of any financial worries.
让我们研究一下这所谓的意外
Let us examine this so-called accident.
首先，你丈夫在保密情况下...
First, your husband takes out
购了保险，为什么？
this policy in absolute secrecy. Why?
因为他不希望家人...
Because he doesn't want his family
怀疑他的用意
to suspect what he intends to do.
-什么用意？     -接着，他独身一人出门
Do what? Next, he goes on this trip entirely alone.
他必须独身一人
He has to be alone.
他蹒跚一路，走到观景台
He hobbles all the way out to the observation platform.
腿打了石膏很不方便
Very unlikely with his leg in a cast,
他必有很重要的理由
unless he has a very strong reason.
到达后，发现不只他一人，有个人在那
Once there, he finds he is not alone. There is a man there.
他叫什么名字，基斯？
What was his name, Keyes?
他叫杰克逊    可能还叫这名
His name was Jackson. Probably still is.
于是他打发了杰克逊
So he gets rid of this Jackson
用些关于雪茄的简单借口
with some flimsy excuse about cigars.
然后他就独自一人了，然后他就做了。    -做什么？
And then he is alone. And then he does it. Does what?
跳了，自杀。这种情况下，公司不负责。
He jumps. Suicide. In which case, the company is not liable.
当然你知道。现在，我们可以上法庭...
You know that, of course. Now, we could go to court...
我一无所知，事实上，我都不知道为何来这里
I don't know anything. In fact, I don't know why I came here.
请稍等一下
Just a moment, please.
我说可以上法庭，没说我们想上
I said we could go to court. I didn't say we want to.
我的建议是双方都妥协一下，
What I want to suggest is a compromise on both sides.
一定金额的协议，一部分的保单价值
A settlement for a certain sum, a part of the policy value.
别麻烦了，诺顿先生
Don't bother, Mr. Norton.
我进来时，不知道你们欠我钱
When I came in here, I had no idea you owed me any money.
你说你们欠我钱，又说你们没有
You told me you did. Then you told me you didn't.
现在又告诉我你们想付一部分，还是什么的
Now you tell me you want to pay me a part of it, whatever it is.
你居然在这时候跟我讨价还价
You want to bargain with me, at a time like this.
我不喜欢你对我丈夫的猜测
I don't like your insinuations about my husband,
也不喜欢你的手法
and I don't like your methods.
事实上，我不喜欢你，诺顿先生。再见，各位
In fact, I don't like you, Mr. Norton. Goodbye, gentlemen.
干的漂亮，诺顿先生。你带球不错，
Nice going, Mr. Norton. You sure carried that ball.
不过射门时摔倒
Only you fumbled on the goal line.
又因为非法向前传球犯规
Then you heaved an illegal forward pass
被处分后退40码
and got thrown for a 40-yard loss.
现在你爬不起来了
Now you can't pick yourself up
因为你站不住脚
because you haven't got a leg to stand on.
是吗？她可以上法庭
I haven't, eh? She can go to court
我们来证明是自杀
and we can prove it was suicide.
哦，可以吗？
Oh, can we?
诺顿先生
Mr. Norton,
我的第一反应也是自杀
the first thing that struck me was that suicide angle.
但三秒之后，我就将这个想法
Only I dumped it into the wastepaper basket
扔进废纸篓
just three seconds later.
你看，你有时也要看看...
You know, you ought to take a look
自杀的统计数据
at the statistics on suicide sometime.
你也许会学到有关保险业的一点东西
You might learn a little something about the insurance business.
基斯先生，我在保险业中长大
Mr. Keyes, I was raised in the insurance business.
是啊，在前台。
Yeah, in the front office.
你一辈子没看过一张保险精算表，
Come now, you've never read an actuarial table
不是吗？
in your life, have you?
怎么呢，他们在自杀方面就有10大卷
Why, they've got 10 volumes on suicide alone.
自杀按种族、肤色、职业
Suicide by race, by color, by occupation...
性别、年中季节、日中时刻分类
by sex, by seasons of the year, by time of day.
自杀方法呢？
Suicide, how committed?
服毒，枪击，溺水，跳跃
By poisons, by firearms, by drowning, by leaps.
服毒自杀，按毒药品种分类...
Suicide by poison, subdivided by types of poison...
腐蚀性的，刺激性的，全身性的，气体性的，麻醉性的
such as corrosive, irritant, systemic, gaseous, narcotic...
生物碱类，蛋白类等等
alkaloid, protein, and so forth.
跳跃自杀，分为从高处跳...
Suicide by leaps, subdivided by leaps from high places...
往火车轮下跳，往卡车轮下跳...
under the wheels of trains, under the wheels of trucks...
往马蹄下跳，从轮船上跳。但，诺顿先生...
under the feet of horses, from steamboats. But, Mr. Norton...
在所有过往案例中，
of all the cases on record
没有一个自杀案件...
there's not one single case of suicide by leap...
是从移动中的火车尾部跳
from the rear end of a moving train.
你知道路过尸体发现地时...
And do you know how fast that train was going...
火车时速多少吗？  每小时15英里
at the point where the body was found? 15 miles an hour.
怎么会有人从这么慢的火车上跳下...
Now how can anybody jump off a slow moving train like that...
还期望能够杀死自己呢？
with any kind of expectation that he would kill himself?
没什么里格楞了，诺顿先生
No. No soap, Mr. Norton.
我们栽了，这次得大出血了
We're sunk, and we'll have to pay through the nose,
你明知道
and you know it.
我可以喝吗？
May I have this?
走吧，沃特
Come on, Walter.
下次我会租套燕尾服
Next time I'll rent a tuxedo.
当时我真该拥抱你，基斯
I could have hugged you right then and there, Keyes...
你和你的数据
you and your statistics.
你是我们唯一真正害怕的人
You were the only one we were really scared of...
但你却几乎成了我们的队友
and instead you were almost playing on our team.
那晚我到家时，已不再紧张了
That evening when I got home, my nerves had eased off.
我再次感到脚踏实地
I could feel the ground under my feet again.
看来将来会一帆风顺
And it looked like easy going from there on in.
那10万块对我们来说就像...
That $100,000 looked as safe for Phyllis and me...
已经拿到了银行支票
as if we had the check already deposited in the bank.
喂？   嗨，宝贝。   当然，一切顺利
Hello? Oh, hello, baby. Sure, everything is fine.
你在诺顿面前表现很好
You were wonderful in Norton's office.
感觉很怪，我一直想看你
I felt so funny, I wanted to look at you all the time.
你以为我不是吗，宝贝？ 你在哪？
How do you think I felt, baby? Where are you?
在杂货店，一街区以外
At the drugstore. Just a block away.
-我能上来吗？   -好，但要小心
Can I come up? Okay. But be careful.
不要让人看见
Don't let anybody see you.
嗨，基斯
Hello, Keyes.
-你有什么心事？  -那只断腿
What's on your mind? That broken leg.
-那人的腿断了     -你在说什么？
The guy had a broken leg. What are you talking about?
迪崔克森的事，他有意外险，对吗？
Talking about Dietrichson. He had accident insurance, didn't he?
-对     -然后他断了腿，对吗？
Yeah. Then he broke his leg, didn't he?
-那又怎样？    -他却没索赔
So what? And he didn't put in a claim.
-他为什么不索赔？为什么？    -你想说什么？
Why didn't he put in a claim? Why? What are you driving at?
沃特，我俩小时前吃的饭，现在还在噎着
Walter, I had dinner two hours ago and it stuck half way.
你的小人儿又开始活动了，是吗？
That little man of yours is acting up again, huh?
迪崔克森的案子有问题
There's something wrong with the Dietrichson case.
为什么？因为他没索赔？
Why? Because he didn't file a claim?
也许他只是没时间
Maybe he just didn't have time.
也许他不知道自己有保险
Maybe he just didn't know that he was insured.
不 ，不，不会是那样
No. No, that couldn't be it.
你亲自把保单给他的，是吗？
You delivered the policy to him personally, didn't you?
-是的    -拿到他的支票了？
Yeah. You got his check?
当然
Sure I did.
-有没有苏打水？    -没有
Got any bicarbonate of soda? No, I haven't.
沃特，我跟我的小人儿生活26年了
Walter, I've been living with this little man for 26 years.
他从没令我失望。这案件肯定有问题
And he's never failed me yet. There's got to be something wrong.
也许诺顿说的对。也许是自杀
Well, maybe Norton was right. Maybe it was suicide.
不，不是自杀
No. Not suicide.
-但也不是意外。  -那是什么？
But not an accident, either. What else?
听好，沃特
Now look, Walter.
有人购买了一份如果死在火车上...
A guy takes out an accident policy that's worth $100,000...
会获赔10万的保险
if he's killed on a train.
两周后，他死在了火车上
Then two weeks later, he is killed on a train.
但不是火车事故
And not in a train accident, mind you,
而是从什么观景台摔下来
but falling off some silly observation car.
你知道这个几率有多高？
Do you know what the mathematical probability of that is?
不知道几十亿分之一
One out of I don't know how many billions.
那人还是断腿的
And add to that the broken leg.
不，不会是表面这个样子
No, it just can't be the way it looks.
-事情有蹊跷   -例如什么？
Something has been worked on us. Such as what?
谋杀？
Murder?
你有没有薄荷糖什么的？
Don't you have any peppermint or something?
-对不起。要点苏打水？    -不用了
Sorry. Want a little soda water? No, no, no.
你怀疑谁 ？
Who do you suspect?
也许我喜欢为自己省点事
Maybe I like to make things easy for myself.
但我总是倾向怀疑受益人
But I always tend to suspect the beneficiary.
-你是指他妻子？   -对
You mean the wife? Yeah.
那个两眼无辜
That wide-eyed dame
对什么都一无所知的妇人
that just didn't know anything about anything.
你疯了，基斯，她都不在火车上
You're crazy, Keyes. She wasn't even on the train.
我知道，沃特
I know she wasn't, Walter.
我没说我知道是怎么干的，或谁干的。。。
I don't claim to know how it was worked, or who worked it...
但我知道事情的确发生了
but all I know is that it was worked.
我要去药店了
I've got to get to a drugstore.
这事感觉就像心里有块大石头
This thing feels like a hunk of concrete inside me.
-晚安，沃特。  -晚安，基斯
Good night, Walter. Good night, Keyes.
-明早公司见   -好
See you at the office in the morning. Yeah.
我本想今晚立刻就对付她
I'd like to move in on her right now, tonight.
要不是诺顿和他公司政策的那些...
If it wasn't for Norton and his striped-pants ideas
条条框框
about company policy...
我会派警察监视，令她晕头转向
I'd have the police after her so fast it'd make her head spin.
他们会将她放进榨汁机
They'd put her through the wringer...
把事情都给榨出来
and, brother, the things they would squeeze out.
只是你没任何证据去进行，基斯
Only you haven't got a single thing to go on, Keyes.
不多，只有26年的经验
Not too much. Just 26 years experience...
所有的百分比
all the percentage there is,
以及心里这块大石头
and this hunk of concrete in my stomach.
能给我一个吗？
Can I have one of those things?
-晚安，基斯     -再见，沃特
Good night, Keyes. So long, Walter.
-他知道多少？    -他什么也不知道
How much does he know? He doesn't know anything.
只有他该死的预感
It's those stinking hunches of his.
但他证明不了什么，是吗？
And he can't prove anything, can he?
只要我们小心，只要我们暂时别见面
Not if we're careful. Not if we don't see each other for a while.
-要多久？      -直到风头过去
How long a while? Until this dies down.
你不了解基斯
You don't know Keyes.
他一咬住就不会放开
Once he gets his teeth into something, he never lets go.
他会调查你，派人跟踪你
He'll investigate you, have you shadowed.
他会从现在起时刻盯着你
He'll watch you every minute from now on.
-你害怕吗，宝贝？  -我很害怕
You afraid, baby? Yes, I'm afraid.
不是怕基斯，而是害怕我们
But not of Keyes. I'm afraid of us.
我们已经变了
We're not the same anymore.
我们干这事是为了在一起
We did it so we could be together,
但这却将我们分开
but instead of that it's pulling us apart.
-不是吗，沃特？     -你在说什么？
Isn't it, Walter? What are you talking about?
而且你并不真在乎我们是否见面
And you don't really care whether we see each other or not.
别这样说，宝贝
Shut up, baby.
太平洋保险。午安
Pacific All Risk. Good afternoon.
你好，奈夫先生
Hello, Mr. Neff.
-你好     -我是萝拉.迪崔克森
Hello. Lola Dietrichson.
-你不记得我吗？   -当然记得
Don't you remember me? Yes. Yes, of course.
我能跟你谈一会儿吗？
Could I talk with you just a few minutes?
有没有地方可以单独谈？
Somewhere where we could be alone?
有，来我的办公室
Oh, yes. Come into my office.
是关于最近的事吗？
Is it something about what happened?
是，奈夫先生，有关我父亲的死
Yes, Mr. Neff. It's about my father's death.
我很抱歉，迪崔克森小姐
I'm terribly sorry, Miss Dietrichson.
路，我可以单独用一会儿办公室吗？
Lou, do you mind if I use the office alone for a few minutes?
没问题，沃特
No. It's all yours, Walter.
看着我，奈夫先生
Look at me, Mr. Neff.
我没疯，没歇斯底里，甚至没哭
I'm not crazy. I'm not hysterical. I'm not even crying.
但我有种事有蹊跷的糟糕感觉
But I have the awful feeling that something is wrong...
我曾有过这种感觉，在我母亲死时
and I had that same feeling once before, when my mother died.
你母亲死时？
When your mother died?
那时我们在箭头湖，六年前了
We were at Lake Arrowhead. That was six years ago.
我们有栋小屋
We had a cabin there.
那是一个冬天，天很冷
It was winter and very cold.
我母亲因为肺炎病重
My mother was very sick with pneumonia.
她有一名护士
She had a nurse with her.
小屋里就我们三个
There were just the three of us in the cabin.
有一晚我起床，去到母亲的房间
One night I got up and went into my mother's room.
她因高烧在胡言乱语
She was delirious with fever.
所有的被褥都在地上
All the bed covers were on the floor
所有窗户大开
and the windows were wide open.
护士不在房间
The nurse wasn't in the room.
我赶紧尽快替母亲盖上被子
I ran and covered my mother up as quickly as I could.
此时我听见身后的开门声
Just then I heard a door open behind me.
护士站在那里
The nurse stood there.
她默不作声，但她的眼神
She didn't say a word, but there was a look in her eyes...
令我无法忘记
I'll never forget.
两天后，我母亲死了
Two days later, my mother was dead.
你知道那护士是谁？
Do you know who that nurse was?
-不，谁？    -菲莉丝
No. Who? Phyllis.
我试图告诉爸爸，但那时我只是个孩子
I tried to tell my father, but I was just a kid then.
他不听我的，半年后，他们结婚了
He wouldn't listen to me. Six months later she married him...
我一直安慰自己说
and I kind of talked myself out of the idea
她不会做那种事
she could have done anything like that.
但现在这感觉回来了
But now it's all back again,
现在我爸爸也出事了
now that something's happened to my father, too.
这么说没道理，迪崔克森小姐
You're not making sense, Miss Dietrichson.
你爸爸是摔下火车
Your father fell off a train.
对，他摔下火车两天前
Yes, and two days before he fell off that train,
菲莉丝在干嘛？
what was Phyllis doing?
她在她房间面对镜子，头戴黑帽
She was in her room in front of a mirror, with a black hat on...
往上披一块黑纱
pinning a black veil to it.
好像她等不及要看自己服丧的样子
As if she couldn't wait to see how she would look in mourning.
您饱受打击，迪崔克森小姐
You've had a pretty bad shock, Miss Dietrichson.
这些事是不是你的想象？
Aren't you just imagining these things?
我在镜子里看到她的眼睛
I caught her eyes in the mirror.
有着我母亲死前有过的那种眼神
They had that look in them they had before my mother died.
一样的眼神
That same look.
你不喜欢你继母，是吗？
You don't like your stepmother, do you?
是不是就因为她是继母？
Isn't it just because she is your stepmother?
我恨她是因为是她干的，她是为了钱
I loathe her because she did it. She did it for the money.
但你不会赔钱给她，是吗，奈夫先生？
Only you're not going to pay her, are you, Mr. Neff?
她这次没法逍遥法外
She's not going to get away with it this time,
因为我会揭发她
because I'm going to speak up.
我要将我知道的告诉大家
I'm going to tell everything I know.
你得小心，说这些事..
You'd better be careful, saying things like...
我不害怕，你看着吧
I'm not afraid. You'll see.
对不起
I'm sorry.
我不是有意这样的
I didn't mean to act like this.
你和我说过的这些，还和谁说过？
All this that you've been telling me, who else have you told?
没人
No one.
-你的继母呢？   -当然没有
How about your stepmother? Of course not.
我搬出来了
I've moved out.
我不再住家里了
I'm not living at home anymore.
你还没告诉你男朋友吧？那个扎切提？
And you haven't told that boyfriend of yours? Zachetti?
我和他分了，我们吵架了
I'm not seeing him anymore. We had a fight.
你现在住哪？
Where are you living now?
我在好莱坞有个小公寓
I got myself a little apartment in Hollywood.
四堵墙，你就那么呆坐着？
Four walls, and you just sit and look at them?
是，奈夫先生
Yes, Mr. Neff.
于是那晚我带她去吃饭...
So that evening I took her to dinner...
去了没人会看见我们的...
at a Mexican restaurant down on
奥尔韦拉街的一家墨西哥餐馆
Olvera Street where nobody would see us.
我想让她高兴
I wanted to cheer her up.
第二天是周日，我们开车去了海滩
The next day was Sunday and we went for a ride down to the beach.
她心情好了一点，甚至会笑
She had loosened up a bit, she was even laughing.
我得确保她
I had to make sure that
不会将菲莉丝的那些事告诉别人
she wouldn't tell that stuff about Phyllis to anybody else.
那像炸药，无论真伪
It was dynamite, whether it was true or not.
而我没机会和菲莉丝交谈
And I had no chance to talk to Phyllis.
你像老鹰般盯着她，基斯
You were watching her like a hawk, Keyes.
我甚至不能打给她
I couldn't even phone her
因为我怕你会监听
because I was afraid you had the wires tapped.
周一早上我桌上有个便条
Monday morning there was a note on my desk
是你想见我，基斯
that you wanted to see me, Keyes.
闪念间我以为是萝拉的事
For a minute I wondered if it could be about Lola.
事实更糟
It was worse.
你门外是我世上最不愿见的人
Outside your door was the last guy in the world I wanted to see.
进来，进来，沃特
Come in. Come in, Walter.
-嗨，基斯。    -我想问你点事
Hello, Keyes. I want to ask you something.
既然我们相识多年...
After all the years we've known each other...
介意我来个直截了当的声明吗？
do you mind if I make a rather blunt statement?
-关于什么？     -关于我
About what? About me.
-沃特，我是个伟大的人。  -是吗？
Walter, I'm a very great man. Yeah?
迪崔克森的事，是谋杀...
This Dietrichson business, it's murder...
而谋杀不会天衣无缝
and murders don't come any neater.
一个毕生难逢的周密谋杀
As fancy a piece of homicide as anybody ever ran into...
聪明、狡猾、近乎完美，只是...
smart, tricky, almost perfect, but...
我想我已全部想通
I think Papa has it all figured out.
想通并用包装纸包裹
Figured out and wrapped up in tissue paper
附加粉红蝴蝶结
with pink ribbons on it.
-继续说，我在听    -知道吗？
Go ahead. I'm listening. You know what?
迪崔克森就没上过火车
That guy Dietrichson was never on the train.
-他没有？     -没有
He wasn't? No, he wasn't.
你看，沃特，在时速15英里的火车上...
Now look, Walter. You can't be sure of killing a man...
将人推下，不确定就能杀死他
by throwing him off a train that's going 15 miles an hour.
唯一保险的办法是之前就杀死他
The only way you can be sure is to kill him first...
再将尸体丢在铁轨旁
and then throw his body on the tracks.
那就是说，要么在火车上杀他...
Now that would mean either killing him on the train...
要么...真正聪明之处就在这里，
or, and this is where it really gets fancy,
你在别处杀了他...
you kill him somewhere else...
然后将他放在铁轨旁
and put him on the tracks.
两个可能性，我认为是第二个
Two possibilities, and I personally buy the second.
你比我厉害多了，基斯
You're way ahead of me, Keyes.
你看，沃特，是这样...
Well, look, Walter, it was like this.
他们杀掉那人，他妻子和某人...
They killed the guy, the wife and a somebody else...
然后那人拿着拐杖...
and the somebody else took the crutches
假扮迪崔克森先生上车...
and went on the train as Dietrichson...
然后那人跳车...
then the somebody else jumped off...
然后他们将尸体放在火车经过的铁轨旁
then they put the body on the tracks where the train had passed.
一次扮演，懂吗？易如反掌
An impersonation, see? A cinch to work.
因为当时是夜晚，很少有人
Because it was night, very few people were about...
他们忙着留意拐杖
they have the crutches to stare at...
反而留意不到人本身
they never really looked at the man at all.
是很周密，基斯，但可能有点太戏剧化了
Fancy all right, Keyes, but maybe it's a little too fancy.
是吗？告诉你，契合度就像手表齿轮
Is it? I tell you, it all fits together like a watch.
现在来看我们求证方面的王牌
Now let's see what we have in the way of proof.
唯一曾真正好好看过...
The only guy who really got a good look
冒牌迪崔克森先生的人...
at this supposed Dietrichson...
就坐在我门外
is sitting right outside my office.
我费力将他从俄勒冈请来
I took the trouble to bring him down here from Oregon.
-进来，杰克逊先生    -好的，基斯先生
Come here, Mr. Jackson. Yes, sir, Mr. Keyes.
你的雪茄不错
These are fine cigars you smoke.
-一毛多一根    -就是这意思
Two for a quarter. That's what I said.
好了，你研究过照片吗？
Well, did you study those photographs?
是的，我仔细研究过
Yes, indeed. I studied them thoroughly.
-很彻底。    -你有结论了吗？
Very thoroughly. Have you made up your mind?
基斯先生，我是个梅德福人，俄勒岗州梅德福
Mister Keyes, I'm a Medford man. Medford, Oregon.
在梅德福我们不着急下结论
Up in Medford we take our time making up our mind.
这里不是梅德福，这里是急得很，快说吧
Well, we're not in Medford now. We're in a hurry. Let's have it.
这是迪崔克森先生最近的照片？
Are these photographs of the late Mr. Dietrichson?
是
Yes.
-那我的答案是不。  -什么意思，不？
Then my answer is no. What do you mean, no?
我是说，这不是火车上那人
I mean, this is not the man that was on the train.
你愿意发誓吗？
Will you swear to that?
基斯先生，我是个梅德福人，俄勒岗州梅德福
Mr. Keyes, I'm a Medford man. Medford, Oregon.
开口无妄言，既非妄言，我当然愿意发誓
If I say it, I mean it. If I mean it, of course I'll swear it.
你看，沃特，这就是证据
There you are, Walter. There's your proof.
这是奈夫先生，我们的销售员
This is Mr. Neff, one of our salesmen.
幸会，奈夫先生，非常荣幸。
Pleased to meet you, Mr. Neff. Pleased, indeed.
-你好吗？    -很好，谢谢
How are you? Very fine, thank you.
-不能更好了。     -请坐，杰克逊先生
Never was better. Sit down, Mr. Jackson.
可以形容一下
Just how would you describe
你在观景台看到的那人吗？
the man you saw on the observation platform?
我肯定他比较年轻
Well, I'm pretty sure he was a younger man...
比照片中人年轻10至15岁
about 10 or 15 years younger than the man in these photographs.
迪崔克森先生快50了，是吗，沃特？
Dietrichson was about 50, wasn't he, Walter?
保单上写的51岁
Fifty-one, according to the policy.
我看见的人绝对不像是51岁
The man I saw was nothing like 51 years old.
当然，观景台很昏暗
Of course, it was pretty dark out on that platform.
现在回想，他还刻意背对着我
Come to think of it, he tried to keep his back towards me.
-但我仍很肯定。   -谢谢你，杰克逊
But I'm positive just the same. Thank you, Jackson.
当然，你明白此事必须绝对保密吧？
Of course, you understand this matter is strictly confidential?
我们在洛杉矶可能还需要你
We may need you again down here in Los Angeles,
如果要上法庭
if the case comes to court.
随时奉陪，我愿意为你效劳，先生们
Any time you need me, I'm entirely at your disposal, gentlemen.
-只要费用由你支付，当然      -哦，当然
Expenses paid, of course. Oh, yes. Yes. Of course.
找鲁宾，出纳部的
Get me Lubin, in the cashier's office.
喂，鲁宾，我是基斯
Hello, Lubin. This is Keyes.
听着，我现在让一个叫杰克逊的去你那
Listen. I'm sending a man named Jackson down to you
带着报销单
with an expense account.
我们把他从俄勒冈梅德福找来，
Well, we brought him down here from Medford,
是为了...
Oregon in connection with...
迪崔克森的案子
the Dietrichson claim.
支付他的酒店账单，好吗？
Well, take care of his hotel bill, will you?
去过俄勒冈吗，奈夫先生？
Ever been in Oregon, Mr. Neff?
是的，他马上下去
Yeah. He'll be right down.
没有，从没去过
No. Never been up there.
等等，你玩钓鳟鱼吗？
Wait a minute. You go trout fishing?
-我也许在克拉马斯瀑布见过你     -不，我不钓鱼
Maybe I saw you up Klamath Falls way. Nope. I don't fish.
你不钓鱼，奈夫先生。奈夫...是这名字
You don't go fishing, Mr. Neff. Neff. It's the name.
-在科瓦利斯有个奈夫家族    -和我没关系
There's a family of Neffs in Corvallis. No relation.
我想想，那个奈夫是汽车经纪
Let me see. This man's an automobile dealer in Corvallis.
-听说也很受尊敬        -好了，杰克逊先生
A very reputable man, too, I'm told. All right, Mr. Jackson.
请去出纳部
Suppose you go down to the cashier's office.
11楼27室
Room 27 on the 11th floor.
他们会处理你的报销单
He'll take care of your expense account
及今晚火车票
and your ticket for the train tonight.
今晚 ？
Tonight?
明早更好一些。
Tomorrow morning would suit me better.
镇上有个很好的整骨疗法专家...
There's a very good osteopath in town...
-我走前想去看看     -整骨疗法专家？
I'd like to see before I leave. Osteopath?
好吧，只是这个不报销
Well, just don't put her on the expense account.
好了，再见，先生们
Well, goodbye, gentlemen.
幸会，再见
It's been a pleasure. Goodbye.
太好了，沃特
There it is, Walter.
纸快包不住火了
It's beginning to come apart at the seams already.
没有完美的谋杀，早晚会露馅
Murder's never perfect. Always comes apart sooner or later.
若有两人参与，一般会早露馅
And when two people are involved, it's usually sooner.
现在，我们知道迪崔克森太太参与了，还有一个人
Now, we know the Dietrichson dame is in it, and a somebody else.
很快就会知道那人是谁
Pretty soon we'll know who that somebody else is.
他会出现，一定会的
He'll show. He's got to show.
他们总要在某时某处见面
Sometime, somewhere, they've got to meet.
他们将情绪激动
Their emotions are all kicked up.
是爱是恨并不重要
Whether it's love or hate doesn't matter.
他们无法保持距离
They can't keep away from each other.
他们可能以为两人参与就会双倍安全
They may think it's twice as safe because there are two of them.
但不会双倍安全
But it isn't twice as safe.
而是二十倍危险。他们犯下谋杀罪...
It's 10 times twice as dangerous. They've committed a murder...
而这不像一起乘电车...
and it's not like taking a trolley ride together...
可以在不同站下车
where they can get off at different stops.
他们被捆在一起一路前行
They're stuck with each other and they've got to ride...
直至到达终点
all the way to the end of the line.
而这是一趟单程，终站是坟墓
And it's a one-way trip, and the last stop is the cemetery.
她已经申请索赔
She put in her claim.
我将会扔回给她
I'm gonna throw it right back at her.
如果她敢，尽管告我们
Let her sue us if she dares.
我静待她和那个人
I'll be ready for her and that somebody else.
他们会一起自掘坟墓
They'll be digging their own graves.
迪崔克森太太？这里是杰利店
Mrs. Dietrichson? This is Jerry's Market.
您需要的英国肥皂
We just got in a shipment of that English soap
刚刚到货了
you were asking about.
您今天来取吗？谢谢，迪崔克森太太
Will you be coming by today? Thank you, Mrs. Dietrichson.
-嗨，沃特    -过来
Hello, Walter. Come over here.
-什么事？  -出大事了
What's the matter? Everything's the matter.
基斯要拒绝你的索赔
Keyes is rejecting your claim.
他虎视眈眈等着
He's sitting back with his mouth watering,
等待你提出控告
waiting for you to sue.
他希望你提出，但你不可以
He wants you to sue, but you're not going to.
-他凭什么阻止我？    -凭很多
What's he got to stop me? He's got plenty.
他弄清了事发过程
He's figured out how it was worked.
知道火车上的是另有其人
He knows it was somebody else on the train...
还挖到一个可以作证的目击者
and he's dug up a witness he thinks can prove it.
怎么证明？ 如果他拒绝赔偿，我就提出控告
Prove it how? If he rejects that claim, I have to sue.
是吗 ？然后你就得上法庭...
Yeah? And then you're in court
很多其他事就会浮出水面
and a lot of other things are going to come up.
例如，关于你和首任迪崔克森太太
Like, for instance, about you and the first Mrs. Dietrichson.
我和首任迪崔克森太太怎么了？
What about me and the first Mrs. Dietrichson?
她是怎么死的
The way she died.
还有你在需要黑帽子之前
And about that black hat you were trying on
就试戴黑帽子的事
before you needed a black hat.
萝拉在和你说她那些荒唐故事
Lola's been telling you some of her cockeyed stories.
-她是在见你      -是我在见她，坦白说
She's been seeing you. I've been seeing her, if you want to know.
以防她四处宣扬她知道的那些事
So she won't yell her head off about what she knows.
她只是在做戏，
She's putting on an act for you,
在你肩膀哭泣，撒谎...
crying all over your shoulder, the lying...
别把她扯进来
Keep her out of this.
我在说的是我们不能提出控告
All I'm telling you is we're not going to sue.
因为你不想要钱了...
Because you don't want the money anymore...
即使你能要，因为她...
even if you could have it, because she's...
让你突然感觉自己卑鄙无耻？
made you feel like a heel all of a sudden?
已经不是钱的事了
It isn't the money anymore.
是我们的命。得退出了，懂吗？
It's our necks. We're pulling out, do you understand?
因为基斯的威胁？别骗我了，沃特。
Because of what Keyes can do? You're not fooling me, Walter.
是因为萝拉，你对她父亲所做的
It's because of Lola, what you did to her father.
你害怕她...
You're afraid she
终有一天会发现，而你承受不了，你能吗？
might find out someday and you can't take it, can you?
我说过，别把她扯进来
I said, leave her out of this.
我在说我
It's me I'm talking about.
-我不想被抛弃    -别那么说
I don't want to be left out of it. Stop saying that.
只是事情未能如我们所愿
It's just that it hasn't worked as we wanted.
我们无法完成，就这些
We can't go through with it, that's all.
我们已经完成了
We have gone through with it.
困难的部分已经过去
The tough part is all behind us.
现在只需坚持别心软
We just have to hold on now and not go soft inside...
像开始时那样齐心协力
stick close together the way we started out.
小心
Watch it.
我爱你，沃特，而我恨他
I loved you, Walter, and I hated him.
但我没想过要去做什么，直到遇到你
But I wasn't going to do anything about it, not until I met you.
是你一手计划。我只是希望他死。
You planned the whole thing. I only wanted him dead.
而真正动手杀死他的是我
And I'm the one that fixed it so he was dead.
-你是想说这个吗？  -没人可以退出
Is that what you're telling me? And nobody's pulling out.
我们一起参与的，也要一起抽身
We went into this together, we're coming out at the end together.
我们要彻头彻尾，记得吗？
It's straight down the line for both of us, remember?
是，我记得
Yes, I remembered.
就像我记得的你的话，基斯...
Just like I remembered what you had told me, Keyes...
关于乘电车的事...
about that trolley car ride...
在终点站之前无法下车...
and how there was no getting off till the end of the line...
而终点站是坟墓
where the cemetery was.
然后我想到坟墓的用途
And then I got to thinking what cemeteries are for.
是用来放死人的
They're to put dead people in.
我猜那是我第一次
I guess that was the first time
我那样想到菲莉丝
I ever thought about Phyllis that way.
死亡，我是说
Dead, I mean.
以及她死了会怎样
And how it would be if she were dead.
我那周见过萝拉三四次
I saw Lola three or four times that week.
有一晚我们去了露天剧场后的山上
One night we went up into the hills behind the Hollywood Bowl.
也许听来疯狂，基斯，但只有和她一起...
I guess it sounds crazy, Keyes, but it was only with her that...
我才能放松一点
I could relax and let go a little.
你哭什么？
Why are you crying?
不会告诉我，是吗？
Not gonna tell me, huh?
当然会，沃特，我只会告诉你一人
Of course I will, Walter. I wouldn't tell anybody else but you.
-是尼诺.扎切提     -他怎么了？
It's about Nino. Zachetti? What about him?
他们合谋杀了我父亲，他和菲莉丝
They killed my father together. He and Phyllis.
他是帮凶，我肯定
He helped her do it. I know he did.
为什么这样说？
What makes you say that?
我在跟踪他
I've been following him.
他每晚都去她那里
He's been to her house, night after night.
菲莉丝和他一直是同伙
It was Phyllis and him all along.
也许他和我交往只是为了掩饰
Maybe he was just going with me as a blind.
谋杀当晚
And the night of the murder...
你答应过我不再这么讲话
You promised me you weren't gonna talk like this anymore.
他本应在大学讲座后来接我
He was supposed to pick me up after a lecture at UCLA.
但他没来，他说他病了
But he never showed up. He said he was sick.
病了！
Sick!
他来不了
He couldn't show up,
因为我爸的火车要开了
because the train was leaving with my father on it.
也许我只是疯了，也许都是幻想
Maybe I'm just crazy. Maybe it's all in my mind.
当然，都是幻想
Sure, it's all in your mind.
我真希望是，沃特， 因为我还爱他
I only wish it were, Walter, 'cause I still love him.
扎切提，菲莉丝与扎切提
Zachetti. Phyllis and Zachetti.
他去她家做什么 ？
What was he doing up at her house?
我想不出
I couldn't figure that one out.
我试着理出头绪，但没用
I tried to make sense out of it and got nowhere.
但第二天才是心乱如麻
But the real braintwister came the next day.
是你搞的，基斯
You sprang it on me, Keyes,
下班后，你在...
after office hours, when you caught me...
大堂遇到我时
down in the lobby of the building.
沃特，等一下
Walter. Walter, just a minute.
-嗨，基斯     -站稳了，沃特
Hello, Keyes. Just hang on to your hat, Walter.
-什么事？   -小事一桩
What for? Oh, nothing much.
迪崔克森的案子刚水落石出
That Dietrichson case just busted wide open.
-怎么回事？   -那人露面了，就这回事
How do you mean? The guy showed. That's how.
-什么人？     -她的帮凶
What guy? The guy who helped her do it.
那另一个人？
The somebody else?
-真的吗？    -对，她刚对我们提起诉讼
No kidding? Yeah. She just filed suit against us.
我准备好了
It's okay by me.
等他们上法庭时
When we get them in that courtroom,
我会把他俩撕碎
I'll tear them to pieces, both of them.
-来，来杯马蒂尼，沃特   -不了，基斯
Come on. I'll buy you a martini, Walter. No thanks, Keyes.
加两片橄榄叶
With two olives.
不，我得剃须擦鞋，有约会
No, I've got to get a shave and a shoeshine. I've got a date.
麦姬，我还是认为她喝酒对瓶吹
Margie. I still bet she drinks from the bottle.
你买雪茄时他们会给你火柴
They give you matches when you buy cigars, you know.
你只需开口要
All you have to do is ask for them.
我不喜欢
Don't like them,
总是在我口袋爆炸。再见，沃特
they always explode in my pocket. So long, Walter.
我吓坏了，基斯
I was scared stiff, Keyes.
也许你在跟我学猫玩老鼠
Maybe you were playing cat-and-mouse with me.
也许你一直知道我就是那个人
Maybe you knew all along I was the somebody else.
我得查明白，而我知道去哪查。你的办公室
I had to find out, and I knew where to look. In your office.
致诺顿先生的备忘录
Memo to Mr. Norton.
机密。  迪崔克森档案
Confidential. Dietrichson file.
关于你建议
With regard to your proposal to
监视沃特.奈夫
put Walter Neff under surveillance...
我坚决反对
I disagree absolutely.
我已调查过他在案发当晚的行踪
I have investigated his movements on the night of the crime...
确定他从下午7：15起一直在公寓
and he's definitely placed in his apartment from 7:15 p.m. On.
况且，我与沃特深交11年...
In addition to this, I have known Neff intimately for 11 years...
我愿意毫无保留的为他担保
and I personally vouch for him without reservation.
而且，沃特.奈夫和菲莉丝.迪崔克森太太
Furthermore, no connection whatsoever has been established...
没有建立任何联系
between Walter Neff and Mrs. Phyllis Dietrichson...
而我现在可以指出
whereas I am now able to report
她和另一男子
that such a connection has been established...
确有联系
between her and another man.
这人曾被目睹在7月9、10、11
This man has been observed to visit Mrs. Dietrichson...
12、13日晚探访迪崔克森太太
on the nights of July 9th, 10th, 11th, 12th and 13th.
我们成功确认该人是尼诺.扎切提
We have succeeded in identifying him as one Nino Zachetti...
前医科学生，28岁...
former medical student, age of 28...
住在紫丁香苑
residing at Lilac Court Apartments...
北拉布雷亚大道1228号
12281/2 North La Brea Avenue.
我们调查过他在案发当晚的行踪
We have checked Zachetti's movements on the night of the crime...
发现他没有不在场证据
and have found that they cannot be accounted for.
我正准备一份详细报告给你参考
I am preparing a more detailed report for your consideration.
我深信
It is my belief that
针对扎切提和迪崔克森太太，我们有足够证据...
we already have sufficient evidence against Zachetti...
让警方采取行动
and Mrs. Dietrichson to justify police action.
我强烈要求
I strongly urge
将本案移交...
that this whole matter be turned over to the office...
地方检察官
of the district attorney.
巴顿.基斯敬上
Respectfully, Barton Keyes.
菲莉丝？是沃特。我得见你。今晚
Phyllis? It's Walter. I've got to see you. Tonight.
是的，必须是今晚
Yes, it has to be tonight.
11点如何？
How's 11:00?
不用担心基斯
Don't worry about Keyes.
前门不要锁上，把灯关掉就行
Just leave the front door unlocked and put the lights out.
不，没人监视房子，不再有了
No, nobody's watching the house. Not anymore.
只是不想邻居看见。我说过不用担心基斯
It's just for the neighbors. I told you not to worry about Keyes.
今晚11点见。是的
I'll see you at 11:00. Yeah.
再见，宝贝
Goodbye, baby.
我想我不用告诉你
I guess I don't have to tell you...
11点时我打算干嘛
what I intended to do at 11:00, Keyes.
这是第一次，
For the first time,
我看到了摆脱这团麻烦的方法...
I saw a way to get clear of the whole mess I was in...
同时摆脱菲莉丝
and of Phyllis, too, all at the same time.
对，我就是那样想的
Yeah, that's what I thought.
我不知道的是她自有打算
What I didn't know was that she had plans of her own.
这里，沃特
In here, Walter.
嗨，宝贝
Hello, baby.
-屋里有别人吗？    -没有，怎么了？
Anybody else in the house? Nobody. Why?
-什么音乐？    -街外的收音机
What's that music? A radio up the street.
跟我初次来时一样，不是吗？
Just like the first time I came here, isn't it?
我们谈着汽车保险
We were talking about automobile insurance.
你心里却想着谋杀
Only you were thinking about murder.
我在想着那脚链
I was thinking about that anklet.
现在你在想什么？
And what are you thinking about now?
我已经想清楚了，宝贝
I'm all through thinking, baby.
-我只是来道别     -道别？
I just came to say goodbye. Goodbye?
-你去哪里？    -要去的是你，宝贝，不是我
Where are you going? You're the one that's going, baby. Not me.
这个街角我就要下电车了
I'm getting off the trolley car right at this corner.
别拽词了。有话直说吧。
Suppose you stop being fancy. Let's have it, whatever it is.
好，我告诉你。我一个朋友有个有趣的理论，
All right, I'll tell you. A friend of mine's got a funny theory.
他说当两人犯下谋杀
He says when two people commit a murder,
就像是他们...
it's sort of like they're riding...
一起坐上了电车，谁也不能单独下车
on a trolley car together. One can't get off without the other.
他们被捆在一起，必须继续...
They're stuck with each other and they have to go on...
一路前行直到终点
riding together clear to the end of the line.
而终站就是坟墓
And the last stop is the cemetery.
-也许他说的有道理     -确实
Maybe he's got something there. You bet he has.
两个人要一路到终点，好吧
Two people are gonna ride to the end of the line, all right.
只是我不会是其中一人
Only I'm not gonna be one of them.
我找到另一个人替我完成旅程
I've got another guy to finish my ride for me.
-你在说谁？      -一个你的熟人
Just who are you talking about? An acquaintance of yours.
一位扎切提先生
A Mr. Zachetti.
得了，宝贝，我得以参与此事...
Come on, baby, I just got into this thing...
只因为我碰巧知道...
because I happen to know
一些关于保险的事，不是吗？
a little something about insurance, didn't I?
我被利用了
I was a sucker.
钱到手的瞬间
I'd have been brushed off
你就会甩掉我
just as soon as you got your hands on the money.
-没人想甩掉你     -省省吧，让我来说
Nobody wanted to brush you off. Save it. I'm telling this.
你和那扎切提一直是同伙，不是吗？
It's been you and that Zachetti guy all along, hasn't it?
那不是真的
That's not true.
真假都没什么不同了
Doesn't make any difference if it's true or not.
重点是，基斯认为扎切提
The point is, Keyes believes Zachetti is
是他要找的人
the one he's been looking for.
没等他搞明白状况
He'll have him in that gas chamber
他就会送他进毒气室
before he knows what's happened to him.
-我会怎么样呢？    -别傻了，宝贝
What's happening to me all this time? Don't be silly, baby.
你以为你会怎么样？
What do you think is gonna happen to you?
你是他的帮凶，不是吗？
You helped him do the murder, didn't you?
那是基斯的想法
That's what Keyes thinks.
基斯满意我也满意
And what's good enough for Keyes is good enough for me.
也许我不满意，沃特
Maybe it's not good enough for me, Walter.
也许我不认可这思路
Maybe I don't go for the idea.
也许我宁愿开口
Maybe I'd rather talk.
有时人们会身处无法开口的地方
Sometimes people are where they can't talk.
比如6尺深的地底
Under six feet of dirt, maybe.
如果那是你，
And if it was you,
他们也会认为是扎切提干的，不是吗？
they'd charge that up to Zachetti, too, wouldn't they?
他们当然会，而那就是将要发生的事，宝贝
Sure they would, and that's just what's gonna happen, baby.
因为他今晚会来，15分钟之内
'Cause he's coming here tonight, in about 15 minutes.
警察紧随其后。万事俱备了
With the cops right behind him. It's all taken care of.
那对你来说就万事大吉了，不是吗？
That would make everything lovely for you, wouldn't it?
是，必须这样
Right. And it's got to be done
在你的诉讼开庭前...
before that suit of yours comes to trial...
萝拉有机会开口前...
and Lola gets a chance to sound off...
在他们在庭上让你犯错...
before they trip you up on the stand,
开始把我一起拖下去前
and you start to go in drag me down with you.
也许我叫扎切提来
Maybe I had Zachetti here
他们就没机会让我犯错
so they won't get a chance to trip me up...
我们就能拿了钱在一起
so we can get the money and be together.
很动听。再说一遍
That's cute. Say it again.
他初次来这是问我萝拉去哪了
He came here first to ask where Lola was.
我让他再来。我在做他工作
I made him come back. I was working on him.
他是那种急性子，很冲动
He's a crazy sort of guy, quick-tempered.
我不断骗他说她另结新欢
I kept hammering into him that she was with another man...
所以他会因嫉妒而狂怒
so he'd go into one of his jealous rages,
然后我会告诉他她在哪儿
and then I'd tell him where she was.
你知道他会怎么对她，是吗，沃特？
And you know what he would've done to her, don't you, Walter?
是，我这次相信你
Yeah, and for once I believe you,
因为这够卑鄙
because it's just rotten enough.
我们都很卑鄙
We're both rotten.
只是你更卑鄙一点
Only you're a little more rotten.
你让我去为你搞定你丈夫...
You got me to take care of your husband for you...
然后让扎切提去搞定萝拉，
and then you got Zachetti to take care of Lola,
或许还有我
maybe take care of me, too.
然后又会有人...
Then somebody else would have come along
为你搞定扎切提
to take care of Zachetti for you.
-那就是你的方式，不是吗，宝贝？    -就当是吧
That's the way you operate, isn't it, baby? Suppose it is.
你今晚编的会更好吗？
Is what you've got cooked up for tonight any better?
我不再喜欢这音乐了，介意我关窗户吗？
I don't like that music anymore. Mind if I close the window?
你能做的更好，不是吗，宝贝？
You can do better than that, can't you, baby?
最好再试试
Better try it again.
或许我走近一点儿？
Maybe if I came a little closer?
这样呢？觉得能动手了吗？
How's this? Think you can do it now?
为什么不再开枪，宝贝？
Why didn't you shoot again, baby?
别告诉我...
Don't tell me
是因为你一直深爱着我
it's because you've been in love with me all this time.
不，我从没爱过你，沃特，你或任何人
No, I never loved you, Walter, not you or anybody else.
我坏透顶了。像你说的，我利用了你
I'm rotten to the heart. I used you, just as you said.
那就是你对我的意义
That's all you ever meant to me...
直到一分钟前...
until a minute ago...
当我无法开第二枪
when I couldn't fire that second shot.
我从没想过这会发生在我身上
I never thought that could happen to me.
-对不起，宝贝，我不相信     -我不是在求你相信
Sorry, baby. I'm not buying. I'm not asking you to buy.
抱着我
Just hold me close.
再见，宝贝
Goodbye, baby.
扎切提
Zachetti.
过来
Come here.
我叫你过来
I said, come here.
-我叫奈夫    -是的，我还是不喜欢
My name is Neff. Yeah, and I still don't like it.
你想怎样？
What do you want?
听着， 孩子
Look, kid.
我想给你个礼物，这个崭新的硬币
I want to give you a present. This nice new nickel.
-搞什么？   -如果你能到山下...
What's the gag? Suppose you go on back down the hill...
去杂货店打个电话
to the drugstore and make a phone call.
留着你的硬币给自己买个甜筒吧
Keep your nickel and buy yourself an ice-cream cone.
号码是G0386
The number is Granite-0-3-8-6.
找萝拉.迪崔克森小姐，
Ask for Miss Dietrichson. First name is Lola.
她不值个硬币
She isn't worth a nickel.
如果我要和她谈，绝不会通过电话
If I ever talk to her, it's not going to be over any telephone.
挺牛的，是吗？
Tough, aren't you?
拿着，去打给她。她需要你
Here, take the nickel and call her. She wants you to.
她一点都不需要我
She doesn't want any part of me.
我知道是谁告诉你的，那不是真的
I know who told you that. It's not true.
萝拉爱你，一直都是
Lola's in love with you. She always has been.
别问我为什么。我也不知道
Don't ask me why. I couldn't even guess.
拿着，G0386，快去打给她
Here. Granite-0-3-8-6. Now go on and call her.
走吧。那边
Go on. That way.
现在差不多4点半
It's almost 4:30 now, Keyes.
天很冷
It's cold.
我在想她是否仍然独自躺在房中
I wonder if she's still lying alone up there in that house...
还是他们已经发现了她
or if they've found her by now.
我在想很多事，但已不再重要
I wonder a lot of things. They don't matter anymore.
除了我想你帮我个忙
Except I want you to do a favor for me, Keyes.
我想由你去告诉萝拉真相
I want you to be the one to tell Lola,
在闹的满城风雨之前
kind of gently, before it breaks wide open.
我想你照顾她和那个扎切提
And I want you to take care of her and that guy Zachetti...
让他不用四处碰壁
so he doesn't get pushed around too much.
嗨，基斯
Hello, Keyes.
起的很早啊，不是吗？
Up pretty early, aren't you?
我一直想知道你几点来办公室
I always wondered what time you got down to the office.
还是你的小人儿叫醒了你？
Or did that little man of yours pull you out of bed?
看门的找的我
The janitor did.
他看见你来时留下的血迹
Seems you leaked a little blood on the way in here.
对
Yeah.
不算意外
Wouldn't be surprised.
我想向你解释迪崔克森案子的内情
I wanted to straighten you out on that Dietrichson case.
我明白
So I gather.
-你站在这里多久了？    -够久了
How long have you been standing there? Long enough.
峰回路转的疯狂故事
Kind of a crazy story with a crazy twist to it.
你还未完全搞清
One you didn't quite figure out.
不可能全都搞清，沃特
You can't figure them all, Walter.
对，我猜你不能
That's right. I guess you can't at that.
我猜现在该对我演说了
Now I suppose I get the big speech...
全是重要字眼的那种
the one with all the two-dollar words in it.
来吧，基斯
Let's have it, Keyes.
沃特，你全身湿透
Walter, you're all washed up.
谢谢，基斯，很快就结束了
Thanks, Keyes. That was short anyway.
我要叫医生来
I'm gonna call for a doctor.
干什么？给我包扎？
What for? So they can patch me up?
为我治疗，直到我能站稳？
So they can nurse me along till I get back on my feet?
让我能用自己的力气
So I can walk into that gas chamber up
走进圣昆廷的毒气室？
at San Quentin on my own power?
是不是，基斯？
Is that it, Keyes?
差不多
Something like that.
-我有另一个提议   -是吗？
I've got a different idea. Yeah?
听着，基斯
Look, Keyes.
不如你回床上，假装明早来上班时，
Suppose you went back to bed and didn't find these cylinders...
才发现这些录音带
till tomorrow morning, when the office opens...
然后你想怎么干都行
After that you can play it any way you like.
能为我这么做吗，基斯？
Would you do that much for me, Keyes?
给我一个好理由
Give me one good reason.
我要4小时才能到达目的地
I need four hours to get where I'm going.
-你哪里也去不成，沃特      -我能
You're not going anywhere, Walter. You bet I am.
-我要越过边境     -你没有机会的，沃特
I'm going across the border. You haven't got a chance, Walter.
试试无妨
Good enough to try for.
-你到不了边境        -那是你以为
You'll never make the border. That's what you think.
看我的吧
Just watch me.
你连电梯都到不了
You'll never even make the elevator.
再见，基斯
So long, Keyes.
喂
Hello...
派救护车到橄榄街的太平洋大厦
send an ambulance to the Pacific Building on Olive Street.
对，需要报警
Yeah. It's a police job.
-你还好吗，沃特？     -还好
How you doing, Walter? Fine.
只是有人将电梯移到几里外了
Only somebody moved the elevator a couple of miles away.
他们正赶来
They're on the way.
你知道你为什么搞不清这案子吗，基斯？
You know why you couldn't figure this one, Keyes?
我告诉你
I'll tell you.
因为你要找的人太近了
Because the guy you were looking for was too close.
他就坐在你办公桌对面
He was right across the desk from you.
比那更近，沃特
Closer than that, Walter.
我也爱你
I love you, too.